<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rss version="2.0"
  xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
  xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"
  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
  xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss">

  <channel>
    <title>
      <![CDATA[  The CoReACTER  ]]>
    </title>
    <link> https://coreacter.org </link>
    <description>
      <![CDATA[  Organization website for the Community of Researchers Assessing Chemical Transformations and Exploring Reactivity &#40;CoReACTER&#41;  ]]>
    </description>
    <atom:link
      href="https://coreacter.org/feed.xml"
      rel="self"
      type="application/rss+xml" />


<item>
  <title>
    <![CDATA[  Leaving Before the Beginning  ]]>
  </title>
  <link> https://coreacter.org/posts/20250530_leaving_before_the_beginning/index.html </link>
  <guid> https://coreacter.org/posts/20250530_leaving_before_the_beginning/index.html </guid>
  <description>
    <![CDATA[  In response to the rise of fascism in the United States, EWCSS is leaving for University College Dublin in Ireland. This post explains their motivations for leaving Pittsburgh and moving to Dublin, as well as what this move will mean for the CoReACTER.  ]]>
  </description>  
  
  <content:encoded>
    <![CDATA[  
<h1 id="leaving_before_the_beginning">Leaving Before the Beginning</h1>
<p>My name is Evan Walter Clark Spotte-Smith &#40;they/them&#41;. At the time of this writing, I am a Carnegie Bosch Institute Postdoctoral Fellow at Carnegie Mellon University &#40;CMU&#41;. I am also queer, transgender,<sup id="fnref:1">[1]</sup> and invisibly disabled.<sup id="fnref:2">[2]</sup> I was, until recently, an incoming assistant professor in the Department of Chemical Engineering at CMU, planning to start on August 1, 2025.</p>
<p>I&#39;ve made the difficult, painful choice not to begin my faculty career at CMU. Instead, beginning September 1, 2025, I will be an Ad Astra Fellow and assistant professor in the School of Chemistry at University College Dublin &#40;UCD&#41; in the Republic of Ireland. In this blog post, I will try to explain my decision. I will also briefly outline my plans for the near future.</p>
<h2 id="push_factors">Push Factors</h2>
<p>I do not want to leave CMU or my home in the city of Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania. I am making this choice out of a sense of necessity, for my academic work and, more significantly, for my personal safety and well-being.</p>
<p>Since the inauguration of Donald Trump on January 20, 2025, his fascist and white nationalist regime has taken dramatically destructive actions targeting the United States as a whole, and marginalized members of society within America&#39;s borders and outside of them &#40;<em>e.g.</em>, in Gaza&#41; in particular. Among many, many others, these actions include: the firing of scientists and scientific experts;<sup id="fnref:3">[3]</sup> extralegal termination of research grants <sup id="fnref:4">[4]</sup> and, relatedly, use of research funding to control institutions of higher education;<sup id="fnref:5">[5]</sup> direct academic censorship;<sup id="fnref:6">[6]</sup> efforts to re-segregate major areas of society;<sup id="fnref:7">[7]</sup> banning medical care for transgender youth,<sup id="fnref:8">[8]</sup> attempting to eliminate gender-affirming care for adults,<sup id="fnref:9">[9]</sup> and spreading falsehoods about transgender healthcare to discredit long-established science;<sup id="fnref:10">[10]</sup> limiting access to life-saving vaccines;<sup id="fnref:11">[11]</sup> attempting to tabulate all Americans with autism<sup id="fnref:12">[12]</sup> in a shocking parallel with the eugenics programs of Nazi Germany;<sup id="fnref:13">[13]</sup> destabilizing the American economy through flawed trade policy;<sup id="fnref:14">[14]</sup> and extrajudicially kidnapping and disappearing immigrants and American citizens, in some cases forcibly relocating them outside of the United States to external locations including El Salvador<sup id="fnref:15">[15]</sup> &#40;with Rwanda,<sup id="fnref:16">[16]</sup> Libya,<sup id="fnref:17">[17]</sup> and South Sudan<sup id="fnref:18">[18]</sup> also possibly serving as destinations&#41;.</p>
<p>So far, I have been affected by the Trump regime&#39;s fascist policies in &#40;relatively&#41; minor ways. My nonbinary gender has essentially been made illegal by decree.<sup id="fnref:19">[19]</sup> My grant application is languishing in limbo at the National Science Foundation, having &#40;as far as I can tell&#41; never been sent out to review after nearly 5 months. I have experienced colleagues self-censoring &#40;a topic I plan to write about another day&#41;. On the other hand, I have not been detained at the border nor kidnapped, and my access to gender-affirming care has not been stripped away from me. For now, I am one of the lucky ones. But the fascists are not stopping or even slowing down their nihilistic and sadistic attacks. As a scientist dedicated to sustainable chemistry and a &#40;gender&#41;queer person living with disabilities, I am at personal and professional risk. The United States is not a safe place for me to live or work.</p>
<h2 id="pull_factors">Pull Factors</h2>
<p>When I interviewed for my position at UCD, I was asked &#40;paraphrasing&#41;, &quot;Would you have applied for this position if Donald Trump were not president?&quot; I gave a short, simple reply: &quot;No.&quot; It was the truth. Before November&#39;s election, I had fantasized about living out my professional life at CMU, becoming a deep-rooted part of the city of Pittsburgh. I would not have even considered looking elsewhere, feeling that I had already landed one of the &quot;dream jobs&quot; of higher education. As I said above, I applied out of a sense of necessity.</p>
<p>My answer to the question: &quot;Why did you apply for this position?&quot; was more verbose, less simple. Yes, I needed a job, and yes, &quot;<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Any_port_in_a_storm">any port in a storm</a>&quot;, but if I saw two ports close at hand, I might reasonably have a preference for one over the other. That is to say: there were real positives about Dublin, UCD, and the &quot;digital chemistry&quot; fellowship that I applied for.</p>
<p>Location is the first thing that drew me in. Before I interviewed, I had never been to Ireland, but much of what I knew made me believe that it was a country where I could be safe and happy. The Irish Republic has one of the highest scores on the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Economist_Democracy_Index">Democracy Index</a> &#40;9.19/10.0 as of 2024&#41; and on the <a href="https://worldpopulationreview.com/country-rankings/freedom-index-by-country">Freedom Index</a> &#40;97/100&#41;. While such efforts at quantification are, I&#39;m sure, flawed, these numbers speak to the stability and efficacy of Ireland&#39;s political system<sup id="fnref:20">[20]</sup> and its excellent human rights record.<sup id="fnref:21">[21]</sup> Ireland is a country where academic freedom is enshrined in law<sup id="fnref:22">[22]</sup> &#40;to contrast, in the United States, academic freedom is only loosely legally recognized through judicial opinions&#41;.<sup id="fnref:23">[23]</sup> It&#39;s not a perfect society, with reasonably high economic inequality,<sup id="fnref:24">[24]</sup> a housing crisis,<sup id="fnref:25">[25]</sup> and an understaffed public healthcare system,<sup id="fnref:26">[26]</sup> but hey, it&#39;s a hell of a lot better than fascism.</p>
<p>It was also hard to imagine a job posting that was better suited to my research interests. From &quot;retrosynthesis&quot; to &quot;analyzing spectral data&quot; and &quot;automated closed loop experiments&quot;, the folks at UCD were speaking my language, emphasizing research areas that I already had experience in as well as areas that I have been actively trying to move into. On the level of the School of Chemistry and UCD as a whole, sustainability was a top focus; my research in energy storage, decarbonization, and waste management would be right at home. I wasn&#39;t immediately sure that I would have the support in Dublin that I needed to achieve all of my goals, but I was confident that my colleagues in the School of Chemistry would be excited by my ideas.</p>
<p>As I dug in deeper, I found other, perhaps less obvious things to admire. I could tell that UCD cares deeply about teaching – as an assistant professor, I&#39;ll even be required to obtain a teaching certificate – and that they put in real effort to promote equity.<sup id="fnref:27">[27]</sup> The School of Chemistry has a large focus on catalysis, and they clearly care about collaboration &#40;they specifically asked about collaborations with Math, Statistics, and Computer Science&#41;. I want to believe that this can be a good community for me to work in.</p>
<h2 id="non-factors">Non-Factors</h2>
<p>In addition to listing the factors forcing me out of the United States and drawing me to UCD in Ireland, I feel it&#39;s important to clearly state some <em>non-reasons</em> for my choice.</p>
<p>This isn&#39;t about money or support. My offer at CMU left me feeling well taken care of, and frankly, few European universities can match the level of financial support available to a research-intensive private university in the United States. When I interviewed, the Head of the School of Chemistry even told me not to expect a startup allocation like I might get in the USA.</p>
<p>This isn&#39;t about prestige or status. Yes, at UCD I&#39;ll have the somewhat fancy title of &quot;Ad Astra Fellow&quot;, and yes, UCD is an excellent school with a good reputation, but it&#39;s hard to imagine a university with a more prestigious computational program than CMU.</p>
<p>It isn&#39;t about the people at CMU, either. The CMU community has been incredibly supportive of me as a person and as a scientist. While I am sure I&#39;ll find a good home in Dublin, I&#39;m truly heartbroken to be leaving the single most positive academic environment that I&#39;ve ever been a part of.</p>
<h2 id="where_we_go_from_here">Where We Go From Here</h2>
<p>My vision for the CoReACTER never involved being restricted by place. I always envisioned a research group that could transcend the boundaries of organizations and, yes, borders. I never thought that I would be fleeing to another country, but the idea of having researchers scattered around the globe excites me.</p>
<p>I will not be physically at CMU, but the CoReACTER lives on. Though it will soon be based in Ireland, we will retain ties to CMU,<sup id="fnref:28">[28]</sup> and ReACTERs there will remain very much a part of the organization. I will continue to collaborate with my colleagues in CMU&#39;s Department of Chemical Engineering and elsewhere in the US. I will also remain committed to the students at CMU who I mentor and work with. There will, I&#39;m sure, be changes and challenges that I cannot anticipate as I transition from the American higher education system that I&#39;ve known to the Irish and European systems; when those arise, the CoReACTER will follow our principles to deal with them as best we can.</p>
<p>To those who are choosing to stay and fight in the United States of America, knowing the danger and looking it straight on: I admire your courage and applaud you. I will continue fighting with you until I leave, and even then, I aim to support you as I can from across the Atlantic. To those who are vulnerable and scared: you are not paranoid or out of your wits. Things are dire, and you should prioritize ways to stay safe to the extent that you can. And to those who believe that my response is an overreaction: I beg you to open your eyes to the horrors around you, at least long enough to be shaken into action. Run or fight as you will, but do something, before it is too late.</p>
<h1 id="footnotes">Footnotes</h1>
<p><table class="fndef" id="fndef:1">
    <tr>
        <td class="fndef-backref">[1]</td>
        <td class="fndef-content">Specifically, I identify as transfeminine and genderqueer.</td>
    </tr>
</table>
 <table class="fndef" id="fndef:2">
    <tr>
        <td class="fndef-backref">[2]</td>
        <td class="fndef-content">I have a number of disabilities, but notably, I live with chronic physical illness &#40;asthma, eosinophilic colitis&#41; and mental illness &#40;<em>e.g.</em>, major depression&#41;.</td>
    </tr>
</table>
 <table class="fndef" id="fndef:3">
    <tr>
        <td class="fndef-backref">[3]</td>
        <td class="fndef-content"><a href="https://www.scientificamerican.com/article/national-science-foundation-mass-firings-go-beyond-trumps-orders-sparking/">&quot;National Science Foundation Mass Firings Go Beyond Trump’s Orders, Sparking Outrage&quot;</a> by Corbin Hiar &#40;Scientific American&#41;, 2025.</td>
    </tr>
</table>
 <table class="fndef" id="fndef:4">
    <tr>
        <td class="fndef-backref">[4]</td>
        <td class="fndef-content"><a href="https://www.propublica.org/article/trump-nih-cuts-transgender-research-grants">&quot;Trump’s NIH Axed Research Grants Even After a Judge Blocked the Cuts, Internal Records Show&quot;</a> by Annie Waldman &#40;ProPublica&#41;, 2025.</td>
    </tr>
</table>
 <table class="fndef" id="fndef:5">
    <tr>
        <td class="fndef-backref">[5]</td>
        <td class="fndef-content"><a href="https://www.pbs.org/newshour/education/trump-demands-admissions-overhaul-and-control-of-academic-department-at-columbia-university">&quot;Trump demands admissions overhaul and control of academic department at Columbia University&quot;</a> by Jake Offenhartz &#40;PBS News&#41;, 2025.</td>
    </tr>
</table>
 <table class="fndef" id="fndef:6">
    <tr>
        <td class="fndef-backref">[6]</td>
        <td class="fndef-content"><a href="https://www.science.org/content/article/doe-denies-it-has-policy-remove-climate-change-agency-materials">&quot;DOE denies it has policy to remove ‘climate change&#39; from agency materials&quot;</a> by Christa Marshall and Hannah Northey &#40;Science&#41;, 2025.</td>
    </tr>
</table>
 <table class="fndef" id="fndef:7">
    <tr>
        <td class="fndef-backref">[7]</td>
        <td class="fndef-content"><a href="https://www.thenation.com/article/politics/trump-musk-lift-ban-on-segregated-facilities/">&quot;The Trump-Musk Regime Wants to Make Segregation Great Again&quot;</a> by Elie Mystal &#40;The Nation&#41;, 2025.</td>
    </tr>
</table>
 <table class="fndef" id="fndef:8">
    <tr>
        <td class="fndef-backref">[8]</td>
        <td class="fndef-content"><a href="https://www.whitehouse.gov/presidential-actions/2025/01/protecting-children-from-chemical-and-surgical-mutilation/">&quot;PROTECTING CHILDREN FROM CHEMICAL AND SURGICAL MUTILATION&quot;</a>, Executive Order, 2025.</td>
    </tr>
</table>
 <table class="fndef" id="fndef:9">
    <tr>
        <td class="fndef-backref">[9]</td>
        <td class="fndef-content"><a href="https://www.wjhl.com/hill-politics/trump-agenda-bill-would-block-medicaid-from-covering-gender-affirming-care/amp/">&quot;Trump agenda bill would block Medicaid from covering gender-affirming care&quot;</a> by Brooke Migdon and The Hill &#40;WJHL&#41;, 2025.</td>
    </tr>
</table>
 <table class="fndef" id="fndef:10">
    <tr>
        <td class="fndef-backref">[10]</td>
        <td class="fndef-content"><a href="https://www.erininthemorning.com/p/fact-check-trumps-hhs-review-on-trans">&quot;Fact Check: Trump&#39;s HHS Review On Trans Care Filled With Pseudoscience, Pushes Conversion Therapy&quot;</a> by Erin Reed &#40;Erin in the Morning&#41;, 2025.</td>
    </tr>
</table>
 <table class="fndef" id="fndef:11">
    <tr>
        <td class="fndef-backref">[11]</td>
        <td class="fndef-content"><a href="https://www.npr.org/sections/shots-health-news/2025/05/20/nx-s1-5405013/fda-covid-vaccine-limits">&quot;A stricter FDA policy for COVID vaccines could limit future access&quot;</a> by Rob Stein &#40;NPR&#41;, 2025.</td>
    </tr>
</table>
 <table class="fndef" id="fndef:12">
    <tr>
        <td class="fndef-backref">[12]</td>
        <td class="fndef-content"><a href="https://www.npr.org/2025/05/08/nx-s1-5391310/kennedy-autism-registry-database-hhs-nih-medicare-medicaid">&quot;RFK Jr. says autism database will use Medicare and Medicaid info&quot;</a> by Alana Wise &#40;NPR&#41;, 2025.</td>
    </tr>
</table>
 <table class="fndef" id="fndef:13">
    <tr>
        <td class="fndef-backref">[13]</td>
        <td class="fndef-content"><a href="https://doi.org/10.1177/00224669020360030601">DOI: 10.1177/00224669020360030601</a></td>
    </tr>
</table>
 <table class="fndef" id="fndef:14">
    <tr>
        <td class="fndef-backref">[14]</td>
        <td class="fndef-content"><a href="https://taxfoundation.org/research/all/federal/trump-tariffs-trade-war/">&quot;Trump Tariffs: Tracking the Economic Impact of the Trump Trade War&quot;</a> by Erica York, Alex Durante &#40;The Tax Foundation&#41;, 2025.</td>
    </tr>
</table>
 <table class="fndef" id="fndef:15">
    <tr>
        <td class="fndef-backref">[15]</td>
        <td class="fndef-content"><a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2025/04/30/us/politics/trump-deportations-venezuela-el-salvador.html">&quot;Behind Trump’s Deal to Deport Venezuelans to El Salvador’s Most Feared Prison&quot;</a> by Zolan Kanno-YoungsHamed AleazizAlan FeuerDevlin BarrettJulie TurkewitzJonathan SwanMaggie Haberman and Annie Correal &#40;The New York Times&#41;, 2025.</td>
    </tr>
</table>
 <table class="fndef" id="fndef:16">
    <tr>
        <td class="fndef-backref">[16]</td>
        <td class="fndef-content"><a href="https://www.aljazeera.com/news/2025/5/23/will-the-united-states-deport-people-to-rwanda">&quot;Will the United States deport people to Rwanda?&quot;</a> by Shola Lawal &#40;Al Jazeera&#41;, 2025.</td>
    </tr>
</table>
 <table class="fndef" id="fndef:17">
    <tr>
        <td class="fndef-backref">[17]</td>
        <td class="fndef-content"><a href="https://www.npr.org/2025/05/07/nx-s1-5389739/libya-immigration-crackdown-trump-deportations">&quot;Trump administration plans to deport migrants to Libya&quot;</a> by Kate Bartlett &#40;NPR&#41;, 2025.</td>
    </tr>
</table>
 <table class="fndef" id="fndef:18">
    <tr>
        <td class="fndef-backref">[18]</td>
        <td class="fndef-content"><a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2025/05/22/us/politics/trump-deportations-south-sudan.html">&quot;Trump Confirms Attempted Deportation of Migrants to South Sudan&quot;</a> by Hamed AleazizAlan Feuer and Mattathias Schwartz &#40;The New York Times&#41;</td>
    </tr>
</table>
 <table class="fndef" id="fndef:19">
    <tr>
        <td class="fndef-backref">[19]</td>
        <td class="fndef-content"><a href="https://www.whitehouse.gov/presidential-actions/2025/01/defending-women-from-gender-ideology-extremism-and-restoring-biological-truth-to-the-federal-government/">&quot;DEFENDING WOMEN FROM GENDER IDEOLOGY EXTREMISM AND RESTORING BIOLOGICAL TRUTH TO THE FEDERAL GOVERNMENT&quot;</a>, Executive Order, 2025.</td>
    </tr>
</table>
 <table class="fndef" id="fndef:20">
    <tr>
        <td class="fndef-backref">[20]</td>
        <td class="fndef-content"><a href="https://freedomhouse.org/country/ireland/freedom-world/2023">https://freedomhouse.org/country/ireland/freedom-world/2023</a></td>
    </tr>
</table>
 <table class="fndef" id="fndef:21">
    <tr>
        <td class="fndef-backref">[21]</td>
        <td class="fndef-content"><a href="https://www.amnesty.org/en/location/europe-and-central-asia/western-central-and-south-eastern-europe/ireland/report-ireland/">https://www.amnesty.org/en/location/europe-and-central-asia/western-central-and-south-eastern-europe/ireland/report-ireland/</a></td>
    </tr>
</table>
 <table class="fndef" id="fndef:22">
    <tr>
        <td class="fndef-backref">[22]</td>
        <td class="fndef-content"><a href="https://www.irishstatutebook.ie/eli/1997/act/24/enacted/en/html">https://www.irishstatutebook.ie/eli/1997/act/24/enacted/en/html</a></td>
    </tr>
</table>
 <table class="fndef" id="fndef:23">
    <tr>
        <td class="fndef-backref">[23]</td>
        <td class="fndef-content"><a href="https://www.aaup.org/sites/default/files/Academic&#37;20Freedom&#37;20Outline&#37;20for&#37;20Website.pdf">&quot;Academic Freedom and the Law&quot;</a>, American Association of University Professors, 2023.</td>
    </tr>
</table>
 <table class="fndef" id="fndef:24">
    <tr>
        <td class="fndef-backref">[24]</td>
        <td class="fndef-content"><a href="https://doi.org/10.26504/jr4">DOI: 10.26504/jr4</a></td>
    </tr>
</table>
 <table class="fndef" id="fndef:25">
    <tr>
        <td class="fndef-backref">[25]</td>
        <td class="fndef-content"><a href="https://www.americamagazine.org/politics-society/2025/02/14/ireland-housing-crisis-249875">&quot;Ireland’s new government faces a housing crisis. Is it bad enough for people to leave the country?&quot;</a> by Kevin Hargaden &#40;America: The Jesuit Review&#41;, 2025.</td>
    </tr>
</table>
 <table class="fndef" id="fndef:26">
    <tr>
        <td class="fndef-backref">[26]</td>
        <td class="fndef-content"><a href="https://www.irishtimes.com/health/2024/10/11/more-than-two-thirds-of-patients-on-hospital-waiting-lists-for-longer-than-target-time/">&quot;More than two-thirds of patients on hospital waiting lists for longer than target time&quot;</a> by Shauna Bowers &#40;The Irish Times&#41;, 2024.</td>
    </tr>
</table>
 <table class="fndef" id="fndef:27">
    <tr>
        <td class="fndef-backref">[27]</td>
        <td class="fndef-content">Fittingly, UCD&#39;s motto in Irish is &quot;Cothrom na Féinne&quot;, which translates to &quot;Justice and equality&quot;</td>
    </tr>
</table>
 <table class="fndef" id="fndef:28">
    <tr>
        <td class="fndef-backref">[28]</td>
        <td class="fndef-content">I will remain officially affiliated with CMU as an adjunct professor.</td>
    </tr>
</table>
</p>
 ]]>
  </content:encoded>
    
  <pubDate>Fri, 30 May 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>  
  
  
  <atom:author>
    <atom:name>The CoReACTER; Evan Walter Clark Spotte-Smith</atom:name>
  </atom:author>
        
</item>

<item>
  <title>
    <![CDATA[  On the Properties of Gender Spaces  ]]>
  </title>
  <link> https://coreacter.org/posts/20250428_on_the_properties_of_gender_spaces/index.html </link>
  <guid> https://coreacter.org/posts/20250428_on_the_properties_of_gender_spaces/index.html </guid>
  <description>
    <![CDATA[  EWCSS attempts to construct a framework for gender based on the mathematical concept of space. Drawing from Eve Kosofsky Sedgwick, as well as other theorists such as Judith Butler, they consider how gender categories are constructed from our fluctuating experience of gender, the cultural relativity of gender, and various elements of gendered perception.  ]]>
  </description>  
  
  <content:encoded>
    <![CDATA[  
<h1 id="on_the_properties_of_gender_spaces">On the Properties of Gender Spaces</h1>
<p>As a first-year student at Columbia University,<sup id="fnref:1">[1]</sup> I was required to take a writing seminar. Most engineering students tried their hardest to take a seminar focused on technical subjects. For reasons that now make a lot of sense but perhaps didn&#39;t at the time, I eagerly enrolled in a seminar focused on gender and sexuality.</p>
<p>This course would be my first exposure to the work of Audre Lorde, Susan Sontag, Jack Halberstam, and Judith Butler, among other powerful thinkers in the areas of feminism, gender theory, and queer theory. But among our many readings, one that I keep returning to is Eve Kosofsky Sedgwick&#39;s &quot;Gosh, Boy George, You Must Be Awfully Secure In Your Masculinity&#33;&quot;.<sup id="fnref:2">[2]</sup></p>
<p>&quot;Gosh, Boy George&quot; is a short but somewhat meandering piece in which Sedgwick considers masculinity and femininity, drawing both on the titular <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Boy_George">singer-songwriter</a> as well as her own gendered experiences. What hooked me in, and what found this essay a permanent seat in my memory, was when she stepped out of her comfort zone in critical theory and into the realm of mathematics, of <em>space</em>:</p>
<blockquote>
<p><strong>Masculinity and femininity are in many respects orthogonal to each other.</strong> Orthogonal: that is, instead of being at opposite poles of the same axis, they are actually in different, perpendicular dimensions, and therefore are independently variable. &#91;...&#93; If we may be forgiven a leap from two-dimensional into <em>n</em>-dimensional space, I think it would be interesting &#91;...&#93; to hypothesize that not only masculinity and femininity, but in addition effeminacy, butchness, femmeness, and probably some other superficially related terms, might equally turn out instead to represent independent variables –- or at least, unpredictably dependent ones.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I thought it was brilliant, the most exciting and powerful lens on gender that I had ever read.<sup id="fnref:3">[3]</sup> I was buzzing after finishing the article, and I probably read it twice more within a week.</p>
<h2 id="gender_for_stem_majors">Gender for STEM Majors</h2>
<p>Since I read &quot;Gosh, Boy George&quot; nearly ten years ago, I&#39;ve brought it up at parties, over drinks, on dates, and elsewhere countless times, often when talking to mathematicians, scientists, and engineers.</p>
<p>As a queer and genderqueer person and feminist ally, I want – perhaps need – people to understand gender. This is especially important in a historical and political moment in which the very concept of gender is under attack by the Right.<sup id="fnref:4">[4]</sup> To provide an understanding, to me, means complicating binary understandings of gender, deconstructing gender essentialism, and creating space for the possibility of transness and gender non-conformity. But to do that effectively, I cannot just rip the rug out from under people and tell them that all that they have believed in a lie, a convenient and powerful illusion &#40;Butler has recently adopted the term &quot;phantasm&quot;&#41;.<sup id="fnref:4">[4]</sup> I &#40;or anyone making such an argument&#41; must build a new foundation, a new structure to hold thought and discussion about these concepts. That&#39;s where Sedgwick&#39;s article comes in.</p>
<p>There&#39;s an appeal to &quot;Gosh, Boy George&quot; that I think anyone could get behind. Humans are visual creatures gifted at recognizing patterns and finding meaning through analogy. Gender, being an abstract, fundamentally invisible thing,<sup id="fnref:5">[5]</sup> begs for metaphor, ideally a tangible metaphor, to make it more readily available for examination. This partially explains the conflation of sex and gender that is so pervasive in Western discourse. Sex, while still much messier and more difficult to pin down than most believe,<sup id="fnref:6">[6]</sup> can be defined in physical, biological terms: hormones levels, chromosomes, gonads, and the like. Though not typically described in these terms, sex acts a metaphor for gender; by conceptually binding sex to gender, one makes the abstract concrete. Reading Sedgwick reveals the possibility of an alternative. Gender is not sex, is not XX or XY chromosomes, nor is it a binary or a spectrum with masculine on one side and feminine on the other. Rather, it is a multi-dimensional space.</p>
<p>Most people do not think in terms of orthogonality and high-dimensional space. While Sedgwick can be helpful to the average person, hers might not be the right metaphor for everyone. But I suspect that it is the right metaphor – or, at least, a very good one – for STEM-y folks. Mathematicians can think of the space defined by \(\mathbb{R}^N\) for some large \(N\). Data scientists and chemical engineers can think of the loss landscape of an optimization problem or a machine learning model. As a chemist, I got used to thinking in high dimensions because of quantum mechanics, where orthogonality is a central feature. And so on.</p>
<p>This essay is written to my fellow scientists and engineers, some of whom may not think frequently about gender, may never have read any gender theory, may never have thought deeply about gender at all&#33; My goal is to expand upon Sedgwick&#39;s ideas, fleshing them out in such a way as to ground discussions of gender in and around the sciences. I don&#39;t expect it to be perfect &#40;after all, it is a metaphor&#41;, but I hope it will be a helpful conceptual and rhetorical tool.</p>
<h2 id="there_is_not_one_gender_space">There Is Not One Gender Space</h2>
<p>The first point to clarify is that, in this discussion, I am not describing a single, static space, nor do I think that Sedgwick would have supported such a view. Rather, a gender space can be constructed from a non-unique &#40;but non-arbitrary&#41; <em>basis</em>. Whether we think of Sedgwick&#39;s gender space as ontological &#40;defining in what way people <em>are</em> gendered&#41; or perceptual &#40;describing how gender can be <em>observed</em>&#41;, such a space is certainly socially constructed. Some of the axes that Sedgwick suggests are historically recent developments &#40;<em>e.g.</em>, &quot;femmeness&quot; as distinct from &quot;femininity&quot;&#41;, and others originated in the West and may not be salient or useful in other cultures &#40;<em>e.g.</em>, butchness, a term which emerges from Western sapphic culture&#41; or which are reserved for certain sub-populations &#40;<em>e.g.</em>, stud-ness, where &quot;stud&quot; is a term used to describe masculine Black lesbians&#41;.</p>
<p>Recognizing that there is not a unique construction for gender space&#40;s&#41;, this article cannot hope to describe the specific features of &#40;a&#41; gender space. Rather, the best that I can do is consider general features that hold &#40;I suggest&#41; for arbitrary gender spaces.</p>
<h2 id="human_genders_are_functions_not_points">Human Genders Are Functions, Not Points</h2>
<p>Most people view most of their identities as static, and this includes gender. In the metaphorical gender space, this would imply that individuals occupy fixed points.</p>
<p>As an example, consider someone who is assigned male at birth and socialized and raised as a boy. This boy may view their &#40;his&#41; gender as constant, perhaps because the labels used to describe him are &#40;mostly&#41; constant and because of an implicit or explicit linking of gender and a supposed biological reality. We can assume without loss of generality that this boy is relatively masculine &#40;<em>i.e.</em>, his supposed gender-y point is high on the &quot;masculinity&quot; axis&#41; and is not particularly gender-y along other axes such as femininity and androgyny.</p>
<p>Even in this most normative example &#40;in the contemporary Western context&#41;, gender identity is not fixed. As the boy grows up, he will eventually become a man, with distinct gender roles and expectations placed on him. Whereas young boys are expected to express a wide range of emotions, the range of normative emotional experiences for men is more narrow. Men are expected to labor to support a nuclear family based around a heterosexual marriage, while a boy has obligations mainly to his parents and perhaps other elders. And so on.</p>
<p>We can better understand an individual&#39;s gender as a function. This function generally varies with time, as the preceding example shows, but it can also vary as a result of environmental factors. One&#39;s experience of gender – and, thus, one&#39;s gender-function – may change as a result of the clothes and accessories they wear, the way they style their hair, and/or their make-up &#40;see: drag queens and kings&#41;. One&#39;s body can also impact gender, which motivates many transgender, nonbinary, and genderqueer individuals to seek affirming hormone replacement therapy, surgery, and other treatments leading to body modifications. Finally, a range of contexts outside of the self can influence the value of one&#39;s gender-function.</p>
<p>A mathematician or physicist might at this point ask: what can we know about gender-functions? How do they behave?</p>
<p>Typically, gender-functions vary continuously – that is, one&#39;s experience of gender does not jump and change suddenly. This means that, if one so desired, one could track gender derivatives – how one&#39;s gender varies with time or other factors along each chosen axis. However, I note that there are exceptions where one&#39;s gender may be discontinuous. For instance, some gender-affirming surgeries create discontinuities in gendered experience.</p>
<p>While each person&#39;s gender varies, mostly this variance is bounded; that is, each person experiences only a limited range of gender&#40;s&#41;. From these boundaries, we can define a shape, a gender-y manifold in our high-dimensional space. Gender itself might be constantly changing, but these gender-y manifolds are &#40;more&#41; stable, varying infrequently &#40;for most, at least; some genderfluid individuals might describe even their bounds as changing wildly over time&#41;. In this extended metaphor, these manifolds represent <em>gender identities</em> or <em>gender categories</em>. Our archetypal man, mentioned above, defines himself as &quot;man&quot; and views that definition as stable, in spite of the unstable nature of gender, because he considers only the manifold and not the function that produces and defines it.</p>
<h2 id="gender_perception_is_projection">Gender Perception Is Projection</h2>
<p>To this point, we have mostly considered an individual&#39;s gender – that is, how do they view themselves, and what is their internal conception of themselves as gendered beings? But equally important in this discussion, particularly in light of the ongoing attacks against transgender, genderqueer, and gender non-conforming individuals, is how one&#39;s gender is perceived by others.</p>
<p>We cannot under any circumstances know the entirety of anyone else&#39;s gendered experience &#40;<em>i.e.</em>, we cannot perfectly perceive their gender-y manifold&#41;, and we certainly cannot locate someone else&#39;s gender definitively in any time and context.<sup id="fnref:7">[7]</sup> While I am not so confident on this point, it seems plausible to me that one cannot even perfectly know one&#39;s own gender-function, though such self-knowledge can certainly be improved through reflection. Gendered perception therefore always involves a loss of information. At the same time, the observer and the observed may exist in different gender spaces, using different bases. Accordingly, we can think of perception of someone else&#39;s gender as a projection, possibly coupled with a coordinate transformation.</p>
<p>Often, our projections flatten gender-y manifolds, lowering their dimensionality. This flattening occurs whenever a gender non-conforming individual is perceived by someone who believes in &#40;and can thus conceptualize&#41; only two gender categories. Whatever their manifold actually looks like, it will be squashed into a two- or even one-dimensional space, projected in such a way that it appears either as &quot;man&quot; or &quot;woman&quot;. But make no mistake; flattening and down-projection can occur to anyone by anyone, even when one genderqueer or gender non-conforming person observes another. As data scientists know well, dimensionality reduction is <em>simplification</em>, and &#40;over-&#41;simplification can happen even with the best intentions and a high degree of empathy.</p>
<p>On the other hand, it is possible to project someone else&#39;s gender-y manifold into a higher dimension. This does not &#40;necessarily&#41; amount to an increase in information <em>per se</em>. All gender observation is lossy; the gender uncertainty principle has no exceptions. However, such an up-projection will often result in an increased in <em>perceived complexity</em>. A nonbinary person who has put in significant work to understand gender and to deconstruct their learned binary viewpoint may infer a degrees of non-conformity in the gendered experience of a self-described binary cisgender or transgender person. That perspective, that projection, is not more necessarily more true than the binary interpretation,<sup id="fnref:8">[8]</sup> but it is messier, more nuanced.</p>
<h2 id="two_or_n_gendered_perceptions_may_be_better_than_one">Two &#40;or <em>n</em>&#41; Gendered Perceptions May Be Better Than One</h2>
<p>As I mentioned, it is very possible that no amount of work allows one perfect knowledge of a gender-function or gender-y manifold, and a single projection always entails a loss of information. But what about multiple projections? Multiple people interacting with a gendered person will have different perceptions, perhaps subtly, perhaps radically. One observer might perceive the same gendered person differently at different points in time or in different contexts.</p>
<p>This multiplicity of projections can be valuable. By observing a gender from multiple perspectives, one can get a better sense of it, approaching complete knowledge if never reaching it. For an external observer, this might enable greater understanding, sympathy, or empathy. For the gendered individual themselves, seeing how one is seen can enhance self-knowledge. This is why many trans people &quot;try out&quot; new names, new pronouns. They offer new perspectives for their friends, families, and loves, and then they see if the resulting projections resonate with their own internal understanding of their gender-y manifold. As a personal example, I came to be more confident in my understanding of myself as transfeminine when I realized that I enjoyed when others &quot;mistook&quot; me as a woman, projecting my gender into the &quot;wrong&quot; category.</p>
<p>Of course, knowledge can be either beneficial or harmful. If a trans boy is constantly being perceived as a girl, he might come to a stronger sense of identity through the constant dissonance. But understanding his gender as being greatly different from how it is projected by those around him does not make it any easier to go through life with the resulting dysphoria and may in fact make things much worse.</p>
<h2 id="gender_metrics">Gender Metrics</h2>
<p>A <em>metric space</em> is a space where there is a well-defined notion of <em>distance</em> between points. In common usage, we can see that even the smallest gender spaces are metric; one might say that &quot;boy&quot; is far away from &quot;woman&quot; but relatively close to &quot;man&quot;.</p>
<p>The notion of distance is important in our everyday social experience of gender. Many people experience homophily – that is, they are attracted to others who are like them. Gender is one &#40;though certainly not the only&#41; category with which folx experience homophily. Implicitly, homophily requires that we can compare our genders to others, to assess who is most similar to us or, from an opposite perspective, to find where we belong.</p>
<p>A metric space does not necessarily have only one valid metric. Just as, in Euclidean spaces, we can use the Euclidean distance, the taxicab distance, or the Chebyshev distance, among others, so too can we define different metrics for gender spaces. This is also socially important. Though we rarely express it explicitly, different people may use different gender metrics, resulting in different assessments of who &#40;should&#41; belong with whom. A trans woman, using one metric &#40;say, something like the Euclidean metric, which equally considers all gender-y dimensions&#41; may understand that they are very similar to cisgender women. However, a cisgender woman may reject this understanding if she is using a different metric that &#40;for instance&#41; privileges certain gender-y aspects such as genitals.</p>
<p>Given that there could be many gender metrics, which should we use? Is one &quot;better&quot; than others? As is the case in geometry, I would say that there is no single, simple answer. Different metrics may be more valuable in different contexts, and it is not obvious to me that any one choice is generally &quot;better&quot; than another. You may ask, &quot;but then, how should we determine the distance between genders or between gendered individuals?&quot; My answer: however you want&#33; You don&#39;t need to change anything about your use of gender metrics if you don&#39;t want to. But when it comes to taking actions based on gender distance, such as deciding who should be allowed to enter what bathroom or who should play on what sports team, it is best to defer to the determination of each individual. That is, if individual X says that they have an affinity to gendered group Y, then that determination of gendered distance should be privileged over any other. In the absence of any objective &quot;right answer&quot;, the best we can do is to let each person be guided by their own subjective metric.</p>
<h2 id="where_to_go_from_here">Where to Go from Here</h2>
<p>Do you see it now? Do you see fluctuating gender-functions bouncing around within complex manifolds? Can you see someone&#39;s gender getting flattened, distorted? Do you perhaps have a sense of what basis you use to understand gender, and where you sit in the resulting space? Can you evaluate how &quot;close&quot; or &quot;far&quot; your gender is from someone else&#39;s? If you answered &quot;yes&quot; to even one of those questions, I hope that you can also answer affirmatively to the question, &quot;Do you think you have a better frame of reference for gender now?&quot;</p>
<p>Whether it&#39;s &quot;yes&quot; or &quot;no&quot;, I&#39;ve done what I can. I shared my best metaphor and I tried to show how it works. Now, it&#39;s up to you to carry on. We are steeped in a gendered culture, and un-learning and re-learning gender is a challenging process. And, whether you&#39;re comfy in the gendered box that you were put in at birth or if you&#39;ve already done years of gender exploration, it&#39;s imperative that we all speak up in defense of each individual&#39;s freedom over their own gender-function. Many lives depend on it.</p>
<h1 id="footnotes">Footnotes</h1>
<p><table class="fndef" id="fndef:1">
    <tr>
        <td class="fndef-backref">[1]</td>
        <td class="fndef-content">Now a test ground for American Fascism.</td>
    </tr>
</table>
 <table class="fndef" id="fndef:2">
    <tr>
        <td class="fndef-backref">[2]</td>
        <td class="fndef-content"><a href="https://doi.org/10.4324/9780203699072">DOI: 10.4324/9780203699072</a></td>
    </tr>
</table>
 <table class="fndef" id="fndef:3">
    <tr>
        <td class="fndef-backref">[3]</td>
        <td class="fndef-content">For a more recent perspective on the philosophy of gender, I cannot recommend Florence Ashley&#39;s &quot;What Is It like to Have a Gender Identity?&quot; &#40;<a href="https://doi.org/10.1093/mind/fzac071">DOI: 10.1093/mind/fzac071</a>&#41; enough.</td>
    </tr>
</table>
 <table class="fndef" id="fndef:4">
    <tr>
        <td class="fndef-backref">[4]</td>
        <td class="fndef-content">Butler, J., 2025. Who&#39;s afraid of gender?. Random House.</td>
    </tr>
</table>
 <table class="fndef" id="fndef:5">
    <tr>
        <td class="fndef-backref">[5]</td>
        <td class="fndef-content">This is not to say that there are not visual gender markers – there are many – but rather that the gender <em>itself</em> cannot be seen.</td>
    </tr>
</table>
 <table class="fndef" id="fndef:6">
    <tr>
        <td class="fndef-backref">[6]</td>
        <td class="fndef-content">See this <a href="https://nyti.ms/2ArrhVF">New York Times</a> article by Anne Fausto-Sterling to skim the surface of sex&#39;s complexity.</td>
    </tr>
</table>
 <table class="fndef" id="fndef:7">
    <tr>
        <td class="fndef-backref">[7]</td>
        <td class="fndef-content">In this way, and to borrow another metaphor, we can think of the gender function as something akin to a wavefunction in quantum mechanics. Following Heisenberg, there is always some uncertainty to even the most perfect measurement.</td>
    </tr>
</table>
 <table class="fndef" id="fndef:8">
    <tr>
        <td class="fndef-backref">[8]</td>
        <td class="fndef-content">As trans, nonbinary, and genderqueer folx, we must be careful on this point not to condescend, nor to view ourselves as enlightened arbiters of gender. Though experiences moving through gender space and observing one&#39;s gender from different angles &#40;different projections&#41; can provide powerful insights &#40;as anyone who can &quot;clock&quot; other trans folx or who has helped someone &quot;crack their egg&quot;, <em>i.e.</em>, come into their transness, can attest&#41;, our knowledge always remains severely limited, and we should place trust in others&#39; self-knowledge.</td>
    </tr>
</table>
</p>
 ]]>
  </content:encoded>
    
  <pubDate>Mon, 28 Apr 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>  
  
  
  <atom:author>
    <atom:name>The CoReACTER; Evan Walter Clark Spotte-Smith</atom:name>
  </atom:author>
        
</item>

<item>
  <title>
    <![CDATA[  What If They&#39;re Wrong?  ]]>
  </title>
  <link> https://coreacter.org/posts/20241027_what_if_theyre_all_wrong/index.html </link>
  <guid> https://coreacter.org/posts/20241027_what_if_theyre_all_wrong/index.html </guid>
  <description>
    <![CDATA[  Inspired by a blog post by the mathematician Igor Pak, EWCSS considers mechanisms &#40;e.g., reaction mechanisms&#41; as a form of chemical conjecture. Using a recent example involving electrolyte decomposition in lithium-ion batteries, they explore the process of challenging and falsifying proposed mechanisms and provide arguments in favor of &quot;mechanism hunting&quot;.  ]]>
  </description>  
  
  <content:encoded>
    <![CDATA[  
<h1 id="what_if_theyre_wrong">What If They&#39;re Wrong?</h1>
<p>I recently came across a blog post by the mathematician <a href="https://www.math.ucla.edu/~pak/">Igor Pak</a> entitled &quot;<a href="https://igorpak.wordpress.com/2020/12/10/what-if-they-are-all-wrong/">What if they are all wrong?</a>&quot; &#40;2020&#41;. In the post, Pak discusses <em>conjectures</em>, mathematical statements whose truth has not been ascertained. They could be true or false &#40;or undecidable&#41;, though generally the person proposing the conjecture believes that statement to be true. Pak explores why mathematicians care about conjectures, what makes certain conjectures interesting targets for mathematical research, and the &#40;under-recognized&#41; value of attempting to <strong><em>dis</em></strong>prove a conjecture.</p>
<p>I&#39;m a chemist, not a mathematician, and even for chemists I&#39;m not particularly good at math. Nonetheless, I have a casual interest in mathematics research, which initially drew me into Pak&#39;s writing. But as I read, I felt a familiarity, something about Pak&#39;s arguments that resonated with my views on and experiences with chemical &#40;scientific&#41; research.</p>
<p>This blog post is my attempt to develop those feelings into a more coherent form. I&#39;ll discuss the process &#40;and the joy&#41; of searching for the places where the scientists of the past have gotten it all wrong. My analysis will focus on the idea of chemical <em>mechanisms</em>, which, as I&#39;ll explain, have some similarities with mathematical conjectures, both in form and in their social function in the research environment. I&#39;ll give some reasons why you might want to become a &quot;mechanism hunter&quot; like me, seeking out questionable mechanisms and trying to support or falsify them, and towards the end I&#39;ll provide some &#40;hopefully practical&#41; advice to consider as you study these chemical conjectures. Reading Pak&#39;s post before this one is not necessary, but it is well worth the read.</p>
<h2 id="whats_in_a_mechanism">What&#39;s In a Mechanism?</h2>
<p>Preparing to write this post, I wanted to make sure that I was thinking about mechanisms in a clear and consistent way. I was intrigued to find that the idea of &quot;mechanism&quot; has been of recent interest in the field of philosophy of science. Thinkers have been pondering mechanisms, from what they are &#40;and are not&#41; to why they&#39;re important in science and how they&#39;re developed. In this discussion, I will start from the following definition that has somewhat recently found widespread use: </p>
<blockquote>
<p>A mechanism for a phenomenon consists of entities &#40;or parts&#41; whose activities and interactions are organized so as to be responsible for the phenomenon.<sup id="fnref:1">[1]</sup></p>
</blockquote>
<p>To parse that out slightly, when one posits a mechanism, one is suggesting a set of actions &#40;the &quot;activities and interactions&quot; of the &quot;entities &#40;or parts&#41;&quot;&#41; that, taken together in some way, cause some observed behavior &#40;&quot;phenomenon&quot;&#41; to occur. And to make this even more concrete, I will provide a chemical example. In a <em>reaction mechanism</em>, the &quot;phenomenon&quot; being caused and explained is the reaction outcome — the formation of some product, the decomposition of some compound, etc. The &quot;entities&quot; are the reactants and intermediates that are required to lead to the observed outcome, or alternatively, the individual reaction steps that together make up the overall observed reaction. There&#39;s a lot more to mechanisms than just this definition, but it&#39;ll be enough for our purposes.</p>
<p>Mechanisms in chemistry &#40;and, probably, in other sciences&#41; begin their lives as conjectures. A researcher observes some behavior, but they &#40;or their advisor, or the reviewers of their manuscripts&#41; are unsatisfied with the observation alone. Rather, they demand to know <em>why</em> that behavior occurs. The &quot;why&quot; — the explanatory mechanism — is more than a cherry on top. Understanding why something occurs can help the researcher place an observation in the context of a coherent theory, and this might enable future predictions and developments based on the initial observation. The observation of electron ejection from metals upon irradiation with light was an interesting empirical development, but it was Einstein&#39;s explanation of this phenomenon &#40;the photoelectric effect&#41;<sup id="fnref:2">[2]</sup><em>via</em> quantization of light/energy that would eventually lead to &#40;among other things&#41; the invention of photo<em>voltaic</em> devices such as the now-ubiquitous solar cells.</p>
<p>To answer the question of &quot;why&quot;, our researcher searches for a mechanism that plausibly explains the behavior that they observed. At this point, we are squarely in the realm of conjecture. And, just as in mathematics, a good researcher will then try to convince themselves and their colleagues that their mechanism is correct, or else try to come up with a better one.</p>
<h2 id="chemical_conjectures">Chemical Conjectures</h2>
<p>Most areas of chemistry do not have the luxury of proofs. We cannot, through logic and careful argument, remove all doubt that our ideas are correct. Instead, we must be satisfied with models that are inevitably flawed &#40;but perhaps useful&#41; and arguments that are at best consistent with the available data. However, we <em>can</em> disprove. As the eminent philosopher of science Karl Popper argued, hypotheses and theories can only be considered scientific if they are <em>falsifiable</em>, <em>i.e.</em>, they can be contradicted by empirical evidence.<sup id="fnref:3">[3]</sup></p>
<p>Given the importance of counterevidence to the testability and legitimacy of scientific ideas, one would think that disproving ideas would be a cornerstone of scientific praxis. Pak&#39;s original post provided a quote &#40;also from Popper&#41; summarizing this notion:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>&#91;Great scientists&#93; are men of bold ideas, but highly critical of their own ideas: they try to find whether their ideas are right by trying first to find whether they are not perhaps wrong. They work with bold conjectures and severe attempts at refuting their own conjectures.<sup id="fnref:4">[4]</sup></p>
</blockquote>
<p>I&#39;ll put Popper&#39;s gendered language aside for the moment and focus on the sentiment. Perhaps his assertion is true when a mechanism can be straightforwardly confirmed or refuted by experiments. If that is the case, then it would simply be lazy <em>not</em> to do the extra work to see if one&#39;s conjecture is false. However, many mechanisms are not so easily dismissed, either because it is extremely difficult to gather evidence necessary to refute a mechanism or because the evidence that one can gather is only indirect. If you believe that the performance of your optoelectronic device is hampered by defects, you can go looking, but measurements of defect concentrations are notoriously difficult. If you posit a reaction mechanism, you may be able to look at kinetics or distribution of reaction products to support or refute your claims. Unfortunately, the transition-states and short-lived intermediates that would serve as hard evidence are most often undetectable, even with the best spectroscopy we have today. In these frequent difficult cases, mechanisms can remain conjectures for rather long periods of time.</p>
<h2 id="aiming_to_disprove">Aiming to Disprove</h2>
<p>By now, I&#39;ve hopefully done a decent job explaining what a mechanism is, as well as how and why they function as conjectures. I&#39;ve also pointed to why researchers may not devote themselves to &quot;refuting their own conjectures&quot; to live up to Popper&#39;s image of greatness. Instead of clearing the field and leaving only a handful of stubborn questions for the next scientist down the line to deal with, we chemists tend to litter the literature with conjectures.</p>
<p>But I, like Igor Pak, see great value in disproving conjectures. Pak provides three motivations to pursue disproof in mathematics: <em>opportunism</em> &#40;most folks try to confirm, rather than refute, so one can swoop in on a strong result with little competition&#41;, <em>beauty</em>, and <em>construction</em> &#40;disproof in mathematics typically requires a counterexample, which must be designed by the researcher&#41;. Opportunism certainly also applies to disproving chemical conjectures, while beauty is perhaps too loose and subjective and construction does not strictly apply &#40;one can demonstrate that a proposed mechanism cannot be true without constructing an alternative, though in practice counterproof often involves constructing a new experiment, a new simulation, and/or a new alternative mechanism&#41;.</p>
<p>On top of opportunistic, attempting to falsify chemical mechanisms is an activity that is <em>productive</em> because it is very unlikely to produce nothing of scientific value. In the best case, you find counterproof and get to turn a field on its head. If you don&#39;t find counterproof, this will typically be because you have instead found some evidence that supports the dominant conjectured mechanism. This may put a controversy to rest or else might put an even larger target on the mechanism for future researchers. &quot;Mechanism hunting&quot;, as I&#39;ll call it for the rest of this post, also happens to be a research activity that brings me a great deal of joy and excitement. I &#40;subjectively&#41; find it exhilarating to tear down a faulty structure of logic and attempt to lay down a more solid foundation. That dogged pursuit of truth is a huge part of the reason I became a scientist&#33;</p>
<p>In the rest of this blog post, I&#39;ll illustrate the process of the hunt through an example that I somewhat-recently worked on in collaboration with undergraduate <a href="https://scholar.google.com/citations?user&#61;wJjvLPkAAAAJ&amp;hl&#61;en&amp;oi&#61;ao">Thea Bee Petrocelli</a>.<sup id="fnref:5">[5]</sup> To set the stage, I spent most of my years as a PhD student thinking about electrolyte decomposition in batteries. Readers unfamiliar with battery electrochemistry might be surprised to learn that the electrolytes in lithium-ion batteries are actually designed to break down. Specifically, they&#39;re engineered to react in the first few charging cycles in order to form a protective layer &#40;a &quot;passivation film&quot; in jargon-ese&#41; called a &quot;solid electrolyte interphase&quot; or SEI on the battery&#39;s negative electrode. Electrolyte decomposition is a make-or-break factor for batteries; a good SEI can enable stable performance for many thousands of charge-discharge cycles, while uncontrolled reactivity can lead to <a href="https://www.latimes.com/california/story/2024-10-28/lithium-ion-battery-fires-rampant-safety-fears">disaster</a>.<sup id="fnref:6">[6]</sup> The focus of my research was to use computational simulations to try and understand exactly what was happening during SEI formation. What components reacted when, and how? How did individual reaction pathways interact to lead to SEI layers with particular compositions, structures, and properties? In other words, my job was to closely interrogate electrochemical reaction mechanisms.</p>
<h2 id="choosing_targets">Choosing Targets</h2>
<p>In a sense, my job was easy. Inspired by the title of an early review paper,<sup id="fnref:7">[7]</sup> the SEI has been widely called the &quot;least understood&quot; component of a battery, and that mystery remains because SEI formation is an extremely complex, far-from-equilibrium process with many interrelated reactions occurring simultaneously. It&#39;s a nightmare to study using either experiments or theory. Everywhere you looked, there were electrolyte components that the community knew &#40;or believed&#41; were reactive, but for which the mechanisms were not well understood. There were also plenty of SEI components and structures that had been observed in experiment but whose origin had not been thoroughly explained.</p>
<p>Given so many options of electrolyte solvents, salts, additives, and impurities, not to mention observed or postulated SEI products, where should one choose to focus? What mechanisms are most interesting, most worthy of our limited time? There are no hard-and-fast rules for developing mechanisms, validating them, or refuting them, but when I&#39;m thinking about research problems, I use the following criteria:</p>
<ol>
<li><p><strong>Relevance</strong>. How important is the mechanism in question? If you perfectly understood it, what would that allow you to do? In the case of reaction mechanisms in a battery, I thought about how widely used a particular component was and how one might seek to control SEI formation by promoting or inhibiting particular reaction pathways.</p>
</li>
<li><p><strong>Uncertainty</strong>. Any hypothesis, no matter how strong or long-standing, could be false, but given limited time and energy, one should focus one&#39;s efforts on trying to falsify mechanisms that already appear shaky. Are there multiple conflicting hypotheses related to the mechanism? Does the mechanism rest on explicit or implicit assumptions that may not be valid? Studying a mechanism that is highly uncertain is likely to lead to some interesting results, even if you do not succeed at falsification.</p>
</li>
<li><p><strong>Approachability</strong>. Falsifying a mechanism requires that only one part or interaction in the process does not occur as described. Do you see a way to probe <em>any</em> aspect of the mechanism directly? If so, how many aspects? If not, what kinds of indirect evidence could you gather? The more inroads you have to study, the more attractive the mechanism.</p>
</li>
</ol>
<h2 id="little_salt_big_problems">Little Salt, Big Problems</h2>
<p>The vast majority of lithium-ion batteries on the market today use lithium hexafluorophosphate &#40;LiPF\(_6\); see Figure 1&#41; for their lithium-carrying salt. LiPF\(_6\) has a lot of nice properties. For instance, it dissolves well in commonly used organic carbonate solvents like ethylene carbonate &#40;EC&#41;; that leads to solutions with high ionic conductivity, which in turn means that you can charge and discharge quickly. LiPF\(_6\)-based electrolytes also form relatively stable SEI layers on graphite. Things aren&#39;t all perfect, though; LiPF\(_6\) degrades to form undesirable side products like hydrofluoric acid &#40;HF&#41; and reacts autocatalytically at high temperature, contributing to thermal runaway.</p>
<div class="im-30"><img src="https://coreacter.org/_files/images/20241027_what_if_theyre_all_wrong/lipf6.png" alt="A 3D graphic of lithium hexafluorophosphate, with a lithium ion coordinated by three fluorine atoms." /></div>
<p><strong>Figure 1:</strong> Lithium hexafluorophosphate. Reproduced from <a href="https://doi.org/10.1021/acsenergylett.2c02351">DOI: 10.1021/acsenergylett.2c02351</a>, <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC-BY</a> license.</p>
<p>Given the importance of LiPF\(_6\) for commercial lithium-ion batteries, it is no surprise that it had been widely studied using both experiments and simulations. Over the years, a number of mechanisms had been conjectured in the literature. Perhaps the most cited mechanism relied on hydrolysis. It was believed that LiPF\(_6\) would first give up one unit of lithium fluoride &#40;LiF&#41;, forming phosphorus pentafluoride &#40;PF\(_5\)&#41;. This PF\(_5\) would then react with water — a stubborn, nearly unavoidable impurity in lithium-ion battery electrolyte - to form HF and eventually form products like phosphoryl fluoride &#40;POF\(_3\)&#41;. There had also been some suggestion that LiPF\(_6\) might break down electrochemically under oxidizing conditions at the positive electrode.<sup id="fnref:8">[8]</sup> The thermal degradation of LiPF\(_6\) had been far less studied than the initial decomposition related to SEI formation, but a plausible mechanism had been suggested as early as 2005 by Campion, Li, and Lucht &#40;reproduced in Figure 2&#41;.<sup id="fnref:9">[9]</sup></p>
<div class="im-50"><img src="https://coreacter.org/_files/images/20241027_what_if_theyre_all_wrong/campion_recreated.png" alt="A reaction diagram indicating the formation and autocatalytic reformation of phosphoryl fluoride from lithium hexafluorophosphate." /></div>
<p><strong>Figure 2:</strong> A reaction diagram indicating the formation and autocatalytic reformation of phosphoryl fluoride from lithium hexafluorophosphate, based closely on <a href="https://doi.org/10.1149/1.2083267">DOI: 10.1149/1.2083267</a>. Note that this mechanism suggests &#40;incorrectly, as I will show&#41; that POF\(_3\) initially forms from a hydrolysis-like mechanism.</p>
<p>LiPF\(_6\) decomposition mechanisms were the perfect target for mechanism hunting. Given the ubiquity of LiPF\(_6\), its decomposition is vitally important in the battery industry, and an understanding of how LiPF\(_6\) reacts could conceivably help researchers design additives to promote desired processes &#40;like LiF formation&#41; and inhibit undesired ones &#40;like HF formation&#41;. LiPF\(_6\) is a small molecule that could be accurately studied using computational quantum chemistry, and such analysis could provide direct observation of elementary reaction steps including transition-states. And boy, was there a lot of uncertainty around these decomposition mechanisms. After I had been researching electrolyte reactivity and SEI formation for a while, it became clear to me that the reaction mechanisms for LiPF\(_6\) needed to be probed by a critical eye. First of all, in a laboratory setting, electrolytes were often rigorously dried, leaving just trace amounts of water. Could hydrolysis really be the major cause for LiPF\(_6\) reactivity if there was so little water? Even more fundamentally, hexafluorophosphate hydrolysis has been known since the 1960s to be sluggish,<sup id="fnref:10">[10]</sup> and this was supported by more recent theoretical work examining LiPF\(_6\) decomposition in batteries.<sup id="fnref:11">[11]</sup> This evidence alone didn&#39;t falsify the hydrolysis mechanism, but it certainly made it sound fishy.</p>
<h2 id="designing_counter-proof">Designing Counter-Proof</h2>
<p>Another doctoral student in my research group had tried to study LiPF\(_6\) decomposition using a chemical reaction network approach that we had developed earlier to study EC decomposition.<sup id="fnref:12">[12]</sup> She had struggled to find any pathway that made sense and eventually gave up and moved onto other projects. Thea, who at the time was working with me through the US Department of Energy&#39;s <a href="https://science.osti.gov/wdts/cci">Community College Internship</a> program, heard about this and decided that she would be the one to unravel the mystery of LiPF\(_6\). Thea&#39;s internship was only ten weeks long. I was skeptical that they would be able to make any serious progress in such a limited amount of time, and I told Thea as much. At the same time, I encouraged them to follow their curiosity, and together we dug into the problem.</p>
<p>With so little time, I knew that a complex algorithmic approach was not the right path forward. There was too much complexity in the code that we had developed, too many little problems. Besides, building and analyzing a reaction network is a slow process &#40;at least how we were doing it&#41;. Instead, Thea and I went at the problem by hand, using our chemical intuition to guide us.</p>
<p>Our first step was to show that the proposed hydrolysis mechanism was too slow to be the major driver of LiPF\(_6\) decomposition. The earlier work of Okamoto had already suggested this,<sup id="fnref:11">[11]</sup> but it didn&#39;t hurt to double-check using some more up-to-date methods. This was pretty straightforward. We assumed that the proposed reaction of LiPF\(_6\) to form PF\(_5\) and LiF was correct. LiF abstraction still raised some questions, but there was enough evidence supporting that it occurred that we were comfortable ignoring it. Then, using density functional theory and some clever search and optimization algorithms developed by our collaborators at <a href="https://www.schrodinger.com/">Schrödinger, Inc.</a>, we found all of the elementary steps of PF\(_5\) hydrolysis to form HF and POF\(_3\) &#40;Figure 3&#41;. Our numerical results didn&#39;t perfectly line up with Okamoto&#39;s, but unsurprisingly, we also found that this reaction pathway was way too slow to occur at room temperature. Even worse, we found that every step in this pathway is thermodynamically unfavorable&#33;</p>
<div class="im-50"><img src="https://coreacter.org/_files/images/20241027_what_if_theyre_all_wrong/hydrolysis.png" alt="An energy diagram showing the hydrolysis of phosphorus pentafluoride. Water first attaches to phosphorus pentafluoride, forming an octahedral complex &#40;ΔG &#61; 0.12 eV&#41;. Then, two hydrofluoric acid molecules are released sequentially. The first reaction, has ΔG &#61; 0.23 eV and an energy barrier of 1.02 eV. The second reaction, yielding phosphoryl fluoride, has ΔG &#61; 0.06 eV and a barrier of 1.06 eV." /></div>
<p><strong>Figure 3:</strong> An energy diagram for the hydrolysis of PF\(_5\) to POF\(_3\) and HF. Reproduced from <a href="https://doi.org/10.1021/acsenergylett.2c02351">DOI: 10.1021/acsenergylett.2c02351</a>, <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC-BY</a> license.</p>
<h2 id="daring_also_to_be_wrong">Daring Also to Be Wrong</h2>
<p>It wasn&#39;t enough to say that the LiPF\(_6\) hydrolysis was slow or unfavorable. We had to show that some other reaction with LiPF\(_6\) or PF\(_5\) was fast &#40;or at least faster&#41; and could occur in a realistic battery environment. This was where we had to think outside of the box.</p>
<p>Thea and I went to the whiteboard for hours at a time. At first, we tried to imagine ways that LiPF\(_6\) or PF\(_5\) could react independently at the negative electrode. Could they electrochemically reduce? React with the surface? Could two LiPF\(_6\) molecules interact somehow? When we didn&#39;t find anything promising, we expanded our search. This, I think, was the key insight that allowed us to make progress. Previous scholars, likely wanting to keep their mechanisms as simple as possible, had locked in on PF\(_5\) and water in isolation, but this was an unnecessary limitation. We knew that there was much more reactivity going on, and there was no reason to think that LiPF\(_6\) or PF\(_5\) couldn&#39;t interact with other reactive species.</p>
<p>We wrote down every reaction that we believed was happening in the battery along with LiPF\(_6\) decomposition, based on my own studies and other early reports. We made a list of every known or speculated SEI component and considered how each might interact with LiPF\(_6\) and PF\(_5\), and we settled on lithium carbonate, or Li\(_2\)CO\(_3\), as a good starting point. Lithium carbonate was small,<sup id="fnref:13">[13]</sup> abundant on both the negative and positive electrodes, and it had a number of sites that we thought might be reactive. Digging back into the literature, we found that there were already a couple of early reports suggesting some kind of reactivity between LiPF\(_6\) and Li\(_2\)CO\(_3\) based on experimental data,<sup id="fnref:14">[14]</sup> <sup id="fnref:15">[15]</sup> which gave us further confidence.</p>
<div class="im-50"><img src="https://coreacter.org/_files/images/20241027_what_if_theyre_all_wrong/pf5_li2co3.png" alt="An energy diagram showing the reaction between phosphorus pentafluoride and lithium carbonate. Lithium carbonate first attaches at the phosphorus atom, forming a complex with a low &#40;0.04 eV&#41; barrier. After a lithium rearrangement &#40;ΔG &#61; 0.64 eV&#41;, the complex decomposes, with lithium fluoride and carbon dioxide being released simultaneously &#40;0.19 eV barrier&#41;. Finally, another lithium fluoride is released &#40;0.63 eV barrier&#41;, yielding phosphoryl fluoride." /></div>
<p><strong>Figure 4:</strong> An energy diagram for the reaction between PF\(_5\) and Li\(_2\)CO\(_3\). Reproduced from <a href="https://doi.org/10.1021/acsenergylett.2c02351">DOI: 10.1021/acsenergylett.2c02351</a>, <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC-BY</a> license.</p>
<p>Thea went to work on the pathway, again going step by step. If any elementary reaction was slow or severely unfavorable, we had to trash this idea and move on to something else. But Thea&#39;s initial results looked good, shockingly good. I double-checked her and filled in the gaps where she wasn&#39;t able to find a pathway. In just a couple of weeks, we had something &#40;Figure 4&#41;.</p>
<p>It seemed like lithium carbonate explained &#40;almost&#41; everything. Our quantum chemical simulations suggested that PF\(_5\) and Li\(_2\)CO\(_3\)  <em>loved</em> to react. Our pathway led to a number of observed products and byproducts, including LiF, POF\(_3\), and CO\(_2\), and there were no loose ends or unexpected species. Because lithium carbonate formed from EC reduction, our ostensibly chemical mechanism could still explain the potential dependence of LiPF\(_6\) decomposition, and we didn&#39;t rely on any minority species like water. What&#39;s more, as far as we could tell, our results were consistent with basically every experimental observation of LiPF\(_6\) decomposition. I was positively giddy; this was an incredibly clean disproof of the hydrolysis mechanism, at least as a major factor in early SEI formation.</p>
<p>As reasonable as our mechanism seemed to us, it was still a conjecture, just like the hydrolysis mechanism had been before. This meant that suggesting it posed a risk to Thea, myself, and our collaborators. What if we were wrong? What if we missed something important, some other critical route that is even more favored, even faster, than ours?</p>
<p>But that&#39;s just science. There can be no perfection, and we cannot hold back our ideas for fear of being wrong. Thea and I came up with a bold conjecture, and we tried to find flaws in it. Maybe we&#39;re not Popper&#39;s great scientists &#40;not least of which because we&#39;re not men&#41;, but we put in our due diligence. Nearly two years since our the paper was published,<sup id="fnref:16">[16]</sup> I still think that the mechanism that we reported is reasonable. Besides, if we are wrong, I would not want to take the fun of demonstrating that away from my fellow mechanism hunters&#33;</p>
<div class="im-50"><img src="https://coreacter.org/_files/images/20241027_what_if_theyre_all_wrong/acid_formation.png" alt="An energy diagram for three reactions between phosphoryl fluoride and inorganic carbonates a&#41; carbonic acid, b&#41; lithium bicarbonate, and c&#41; lithium carbonate to form PF2OOH, &#40;a&#41;, LiPO2F2 &#40;c&#41;, or a complex &#40;b&#41;. Only the reaction with lithium carbonate is thermodynamically favored; as shown in d&#41;, this can be attributed to the partial charge of the carbonate oxygens, which is a proxy for basicity. The more negative the oxygen &#40;or, the more basic the carbonate&#41;, the more reactive the molecule with phosphoryl fluoride." /></div>
<p><strong>Figure 5:</strong> An energy diagram for three reactions between POF\(_3\) and inorganic carbonates a&#41; H\(_2\)CO\(_3\), b&#41; LiHCO\(_3\), and c&#41; Li\(_2\)CO\(_3\). The thermodynamic favorability of these reactions is rationalized in d&#41; via the inorganic carbonate oxygen partial charge, which is a proxy for basicity. Reproduced from <a href="https://doi.org/10.1021/acsenergylett.2c02351">DOI: 10.1021/acsenergylett.2c02351</a>, <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC-BY</a> license.</p>
<h2 id="sometimes_they_get_it_right">Sometimes, They Get It Right</h2>
<p>Above, I mentioned that LiPF\(_6\) autocatalyzes at high temperature and that a mechanism for this process had been conjectured by Brett Lucht&#39;s group a few decades back. After Thea and I had disproven the hydrolysis mechanism, we thought that we might take a swing at autocatalysis, as well. We had less of a clear reason to think this mechanism was incorrect &#40;this mechanism did not meet our second criterion, uncertainty, very well&#41;, but it had not been closely studied by theory since its proposal.</p>
<p>I will spare you the details of our search; suffice to say that we more or less followed the lead of Campion et al., filling in some gaps where necessary and considering multiple &#40;simple&#41; chemical terminations to try and cover our bases. In the end, we found that the Campion mechanism was slightly simplified but didn&#39;t have any major flaws &#40;compare Figure 5 and Figure 6 to Figure 2 above&#41;.</p>
<div class="im-50"><img src="https://coreacter.org/_files/images/20241027_what_if_theyre_all_wrong/reformation.png" alt="An energy diagram showing the reaction between phosphorus pentafluoride and either PF2OOH &#40;a&#41; or LiPO2F2 &#40;b&#41;. Both reactions are sluggish, with intramolecular fluorine transfer being the rate-limiting step. c&#41; and d&#41; show the rate coefficients of these rate-limiting steps as a function of temperature. The reaction with PF2OOH has an appreciable rate around 150 C, while the reaction with LiPO2F2 remains sluggish." /></div>
<p><strong>Figure 6:</strong> An energy diagram for the reaction between PF\(_5\) and a&#41; PF\(_2\)OOH or b&#41; LiPF\(_2\)O\(_2\), formed in the reactions shown in Figure 5. Rate coefficients for the rate-limiting intramolecular fluoride transfer steps are shown in c&#41; and d&#41; as a function of temperature. Reproduced from <a href="https://doi.org/10.1021/acsenergylett.2c02351">DOI: 10.1021/acsenergylett.2c02351</a>, <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC-BY</a> license.</p>
<p>But even a failed mechanism hunt is still productive, and this is no exception. Thea and I may not have ripped any holes in Campion et al.&#39;s mechanism, but we were able to support this mechanism and find something new to say about it. Specifically, we learned that the reason why LiPF\(_6\) needs high temperatures to autocatalyze is based on one really slow step where a fluorine atom hops from one side of a complex to the other. We also found that the autocatalysis was much easier if protons were involved, which might implicate water &#40;Remember: we found that water and PF\(_5\) react slowly under normal operating conditions. High temperature is a different story&#33;&#41;. These results weren&#39;t huge deals, but we walked away from our analysis feeling like our time was well spent.</p>
<h2 id="leaving_gaps_behind">Leaving Gaps Behind</h2>
<p>Of course, in chemistry as in many fields, every good answer leaves behind questions. Thea and I did a great job knocking down the hydrolysis mechanism, but we didn&#39;t explain everything. The most important question that our analysis left behind involved HF. There&#39;s strong experimental evidence that it forms in batteries, and in fact, it can be seriously harmful to a battery&#39;s health. Yet HF doesn&#39;t show up anywhere in out analysis; what gives?</p>
<p>The honest answer is: we don&#39;t know&#33; We&#39;re pretty confident that HF isn&#39;t coming from chemical reactions with water, and earlier reports of electrochemical HF formation don&#39;t seem much better &#40;the calculated oxidation potentials of PF\(_6^-\) and water, which are usually pretty reliable, are way too high to be relevant to any normal battery&#41;.<sup id="fnref:8">[8]</sup></p>
<p>Some scientist more clever or more dedicated than me will, in all likelihood, eventually cook up a reasonable mechanism. Maybe it&#39;ll be you, dear Reader. And when they &#40;you&#41; do, I&#39;ll be overjoyed&#33; There&#39;s no shame in leaving questions for someone else to answer, in my opinion; quite the opposite. As I wrote in the dedication of my dissertation: &quot;to the brighter minds who will prove me wrong and find better paths than I could dream up. I left you plenty of fuel. Find something fun to burn.&quot;</p>
<h2 id="what_should_you_do">What Should You Do?</h2>
<p>So you want to be a mechanism hunter? My advice to you would be this:</p>
<ol>
<li><p><strong>Look at every mechanism critically</strong>. What are the authors assuming? What evidence do they use to support their mechanism? Does the mechanism appear to be in contradiction with any evidence that you&#39;re aware of? Remember that conjectures, even ones put forward by leading experts, are disproven all the time.</p>
</li>
<li><p><strong>Find the gaps in analysis</strong>. What haven&#39;t previous studies considered about a given process? Can you think of experiments or simulations that you could use to make initial probes of the conjectured mechanism?</p>
</li>
<li><p><strong>Understand yourself</strong> Here, I&#39;m once again shamelessly stealing from Pak&#39;s post. Every scientist has a specialized set of tools and techniques that they&#39;re familiar with. Once you&#39;ve found a problem worth studying, consider if and how your tools might be used to study it. Just because you&#39;ve found a mechanism worthy of attack does not necessarily mean that you should be the one to attack it. Save your energy for the tasks you are best suited for.</p>
</li>
<li><p><strong>Make conjectures, but make them carefully</strong>. Aspire to be like Popper&#39;s scientist, and try to refute your own ideas before you release them into the world. You may still be wrong, but if you are, you can hold your head high and say that you did what you could to explain.</p>
</li>
<li><p><strong>Fear not incorrectness</strong>. Absolute proof in the chemical sciences is rare and elusive. Even your best, most solid mechanism might be flawed, as might your attempts to confirm or falsify someone else&#39;s mechanisms. You gain nothing by being timid and holding back. Even if you are wrong, by giving into fear, you take away other mechanism hunters&#39; fun.</p>
</li>
</ol>
<h1 id="footnotes">Footnotes</h1>
<p><table class="fndef" id="fndef:1">
    <tr>
        <td class="fndef-backref">[1]</td>
        <td class="fndef-content"><a href="https://doi.org/10.1093/oso/9780198779711.001.0001">DOI: 10.1093/oso/9780198779711.001.0001</a></td>
    </tr>
</table>
<table class="fndef" id="fndef:2">
    <tr>
        <td class="fndef-backref">[2]</td>
        <td class="fndef-content"><a href="https://doi.org/10.1002/andp.19053220607">DOI: 10.1002/andp.19053220607</a></td>
    </tr>
</table>
<table class="fndef" id="fndef:3">
    <tr>
        <td class="fndef-backref">[3]</td>
        <td class="fndef-content"><a href="https://doi.org/10.4324/9780203994627">DOI: 10.4324/9780203994627</a></td>
    </tr>
</table>
<table class="fndef" id="fndef:4">
    <tr>
        <td class="fndef-backref">[4]</td>
        <td class="fndef-content">From &quot;Replies to My Critics&quot;, presented in <em>The Philosophy of Karl Popper, Part 2</em> &#40;1974&#41;.</td>
    </tr>
</table>
<table class="fndef" id="fndef:5">
    <tr>
        <td class="fndef-backref">[5]</td>
        <td class="fndef-content">Thea is applying for PhD positions this year. Look out for their applications&#33;</td>
    </tr>
</table>
<table class="fndef" id="fndef:6">
    <tr>
        <td class="fndef-backref">[6]</td>
        <td class="fndef-content">I picked one news article that had just been published when I was writing this post. Search &quot;lithium-ion battery fire&quot; or &quot;lithium-ion battery explosion&quot; and you&#39;ll find plenty more.</td>
    </tr>
</table>
<table class="fndef" id="fndef:7">
    <tr>
        <td class="fndef-backref">[7]</td>
        <td class="fndef-content"><a href="https://doi.org/10.1524/zpch.2009.6086">DOI: 10.1524/zpch.2009.6086</a></td>
    </tr>
</table>
<table class="fndef" id="fndef:8">
    <tr>
        <td class="fndef-backref">[8]</td>
        <td class="fndef-content"><a href="https://doi.org/10.1021/acsenergylett.1c00707">DOI: 10.1021/acsenergylett.1c00707</a></td>
    </tr>
</table>
<table class="fndef" id="fndef:9">
    <tr>
        <td class="fndef-backref">[9]</td>
        <td class="fndef-content"><a href="https://doi.org/10.1149/1.2083267">DOI: 10.1149/1.2083267</a></td>
    </tr>
</table>
<table class="fndef" id="fndef:10">
    <tr>
        <td class="fndef-backref">[10]</td>
        <td class="fndef-content"><a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/0022-1902&#40;69&#41;80024-2">DOI: 10.1016/0022-1902&#40;69&#41;80024-2</a></td>
    </tr>
</table>
<table class="fndef" id="fndef:11">
    <tr>
        <td class="fndef-backref">[11]</td>
        <td class="fndef-content"><a href="https://doi.org/10.1149/2.020303jes">DOI: 10.1149/2.020303jes</a></td>
    </tr>
</table>
<table class="fndef" id="fndef:12">
    <tr>
        <td class="fndef-backref">[12]</td>
        <td class="fndef-content"><a href="https://doi.org/10.1039/D0SC05647B">DOI: 10.1039/D0SC05647B</a></td>
    </tr>
</table>
<table class="fndef" id="fndef:13">
    <tr>
        <td class="fndef-backref">[13]</td>
        <td class="fndef-content">Read: &#40;relatively&#41; easy to study.</td>
    </tr>
</table>
<table class="fndef" id="fndef:14">
    <tr>
        <td class="fndef-backref">[14]</td>
        <td class="fndef-content"><a href="https://doi.org/10.1039/C6RA00648E">DOI: 10.1039/C6RA00648E</a></td>
    </tr>
</table>
<table class="fndef" id="fndef:15">
    <tr>
        <td class="fndef-backref">[15]</td>
        <td class="fndef-content"><a href="https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.jpcc.7b08433">DOI: 10.1021/acs.jpcc.7b08433</a></td>
    </tr>
</table>
<table class="fndef" id="fndef:16">
    <tr>
        <td class="fndef-backref">[16]</td>
        <td class="fndef-content"><a href="https://doi.org/10.1021/acsenergylett.2c02351">DOI: 10.1021/acsenergylett.2c02351</a></td>
    </tr>
</table>
</p>
 ]]>
  </content:encoded>
    
  <pubDate>Mon, 06 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>  
  
  
  <atom:author>
    <atom:name>The CoReACTER; Evan Walter Clark Spotte-Smith</atom:name>
  </atom:author>
        
</item>

<item>
  <title>
    <![CDATA[  Foundations of Chemical Ethics: 0. Foundations of the Foundations  ]]>
  </title>
  <link> https://coreacter.org/posts/20241204_ethical_foundations_0/index.html </link>
  <guid> https://coreacter.org/posts/20241204_ethical_foundations_0/index.html </guid>
  <description>
    <![CDATA[  In this preview, EWCSS introduces a new series on ethics in the chemical sciences. They discuss their motivations for embarking on this journey, their intended scope and goals, and they raise some possible directions for future posts.  ]]>
  </description>  
  
  <content:encoded>
    <![CDATA[  
<h1 id="foundations_of_chemical_ethics">Foundations of Chemical Ethics</h1>
<h1 id="0_foundations_of_the_foundations">0: Foundations of the Foundations</h1>
<p>This blog post is the first &#40;or, really, the zeroth&#41; in a series on &quot;chemical ethics&quot;. However, I won&#39;t be getting into the weeds of any serious ethical arguments quite yet. Rather, I want to take this blog post to explain why I&#39;m interested in this topic and what I hope to accomplish by writing about ethics.</p>
<h2 id="motivations">Motivations</h2>
<p>My reasons for starting this series are simple: 1&#41; I belive that chemical ethics is important; 2&#41; not enough has been written about ethics in chemistry; and 3&#41; I care. Here, I will explore each of these motivations in some detail.</p>
<h3 id="the_moral_burden_of_chemistry">The Moral Burden of Chemistry</h3>
<p>Chemicals and the chemical industries have been partially or wholly responsible for many of the great disasters of modern times. Some historians call World War I &quot;the Chemist&#39;s War&quot; because of the widespread use of chemical weapons, which killed nearly 100,000 and injured over 1 million people.<sup id="fnref:1">[1]</sup> Chemical weapons use decreased considerably after the first World War &#40;though never going away completely&#41;.<sup id="fnref:2">[2]</sup> Nonetheless, chemistry has remained important in warfare, with the use of synthetic herbicides &#40;e.g., &quot;<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Agent_Orange">Agent Orange</a>&quot;&#41; in the Vietnam War being perhaps the most salient in the American memory. In Vietnam, herbicides were meant to starve the North Vietnamese Communists and eliminate their forest cover, but tactical herbicides also contributed to an increase in birth defects following parental exposure.<sup id="fnref:3">[3]</sup></p>
<p>&#40;Chemical&#41; war is Hell, but there&#39;s many more examples outside of the battlefield. One of the largest medical disasters of all time was caused by a chemical reaction: the conversion of R&#40;&#43;&#41; thalidomide — a drug that can treat a variety of medical conditions, including morning sickness in pregnant people — into S&#40;-&#41; thalidomide, a teratogen &#40;substance that interferes with the development of fetuses&#41;.<sup id="fnref:4">[4]</sup> Chemical accidents like the 1984 Bhopal disaster in India and the 2020 Beirut explosion have the potential to kill hundreds to thousands, while environmental chemical pollution can &#40;less dramatically and perhaps more indirectly&#41; kill by increasing the likelihood and severity of health decline and disease.<sup id="fnref:5">[5]</sup> Important examples of environmental chemical pollutants with severe health impacts include microplastics — which are now ubiquitous in the natural environment<sup id="fnref:6">[6]</sup> and adversely affect human<sup id="fnref:7">[7]</sup> and non-human animal health<sup id="fnref:8">[8]</sup> — as well as tetraethyl lead &#40;a long-time additive in gasoline&#41;<sup id="fnref:9">[9]</sup> and per-/polyfluoroalkyl substances &#40;PFAS&#41;.<sup id="fnref:10">[10]</sup></p>
<p>Finally, I would be remiss if I didn&#39;t mention the elephant in the room: climate change. While many chemical scientists &#40;including me&#33;&#41; work to eliminate fossil fuel use and minimize the impacts of climate change, the reality is that our field got us into this mess in the first place. Not only are chemical engineers major players in the fossil fuel industry, creating the oil and natural gas products that we use to generate electricity and heat &#40;33&#37; of global greenhouse gas emissions&#41; and power most of our transportation &#40;15&#37; of emissions&#41;, but most industrial emissions &#40;24&#37; of emissions&#41; come from the production of chemicals and materials, particularly building materials like metals &#40;<em>e.g.</em>, steel&#41; and cement.<sup id="fnref:11">[11]</sup> In other words, the <strong>majority of global greenhouse gas emissions</strong> can be tied to the chemical sciences and chemical industries. Yikes.</p>
<p>I bring up all of these examples of chemically-induced disasters, intentional and unintentional, to illustrate the outsized impact that chemistry and the chemical sciences have in the world. Our work has the power to destroy lives and &#40;especially if climate change continues unabated&#41; irreparably harm the environment and human society as we know it. Chemistry — and the actions of chemical scientists — has immense moral significance, and thus it is important to determine how such scientists should act. That is to say, chemical ethics are critical for ensuring public and environmental safety.</p>
<h3 id="a_gap_in_the_literature">A Gap In the Literature</h3>
<p>Ethics in the medical and life sciences have been considered and debated since at least the time of Hippocrates in the 5th century BCE.<sup id="fnref:12">[12]</sup> From the basic principle of &quot;do no harm&quot;, bioethics and medical ethics evolved over time as the understanding of medicine and the context in which it was practice changed. In fact, the first modern thinker to develop the idea of bioethics, Fritz Jahr,<sup id="fnref:13">[13]</sup> argued that advancements in science demanded ongoing reflections in moral philosophy.<sup id="fnref:14">[14]</sup> Notably, the field of medical research responded to the Nazi atrocities during World War II by embracing the Nuremburg Code,<sup id="fnref:15">[15]</sup> a set of rules for research with human subjects. The recognition of the importance of ethics in biology and medicine continued long after, as exemplified by the development of the 1978 <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20111017133845/http://www.hhs.gov/ohrp/archive/documents/19790418.pdf">Belmont Report</a>, which establishes respect for persons, beneficence, and justice as core ethical principles for medical research. But bioethics is more than a static set of general guidelines and core principles; it remains a thriving area of research, and many students of the life sciences are required to take courses in bioethics to obtain their degrees. Some schools even offer <a href="https://www.sas.rochester.edu/ph/undergraduate/majors/bioethics.html">degrees</a> in bioethics&#33;</p>
<p>Contrast this history with the situation in the chemical sciences. While individual chemical professional societies have ethical codes, including the American Chemical Society &#40;ACS&#41;,<sup id="fnref:16">[16]</sup> American Institute of Chemical Engineers,<sup id="fnref:17">[17]</sup> Royal Society of Chemistry,<sup id="fnref:18">[18]</sup> and German Chemical Society,<sup id="fnref:19">[19]</sup> there are no general ethical codes or principles recognized across the chemical sciences. In 2016, ACS convened a workshop which produced the Global Chemists&#39; Code of Ethics &#40;GCCE&#41;, but this is a far cry from the Belmont Report. The GCCE includes statements like</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Chemical practitioners should promote a positive perception and public understanding and appreciation of chemistry. This is done through research, innovation, teamwork, collaboration, community outreach, and high ethical standards.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>and</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Researchers should conduct their work with the highest integrity and transparency</p>
</blockquote>
<p>without defining what the &quot;ethical standards&quot; that must be followed are or what it means for a chemist to have &quot;integrity&quot;&#33;</p>
<p>In spite of the moral significance of the chemical sciences, chemical ethics are not taken seriously by many chemical practitioners or organizations. This is evidenced by the lack of academic journals that regularly publish articles on ethics in the chemical sciences<sup id="fnref:20">[20]</sup> &#40;though articles on chemical ethics occasionally appear in other, non-specialized journals&#41; and the few books written on the subject.<sup id="fnref:21">[21]</sup> <sup id="fnref:22">[22]</sup> <sup id="fnref:23">[23]</sup> <sup id="fnref:24">[24]</sup> Perhaps because of this perceived lack of importance, the ethics curriculum available to students in chemical science programs tends to be extremely limited, often focusing &#40;where it exists at all&#41; on generic issues of safety and research integrity without discussing the specific questions and problems that arise in chemical practice.</p>
<h3 id="personal_motivation">Personal Motivation</h3>
<p>So, the ethics and moral norms of the chemical sciences are vitally important for the world and its inhabitants, but the philosophy, literature, and related pedagogy are underdeveloped &#40;compared to bioethics, as well as other fields like engineering ethics&#41;. This, I would argue, motivates <em>someone</em> to develop a chemical ethic. But why me? Why the CoReACTER?</p>
<p>As a doctoral student, I witnessed and found myself embroiled in a number of ethical conflicts. Some of these were specific to chemistry, and others were more general problems of research ethics or professional ethics. While I will not tell any specific stories here, I am sure that I will return to some of these experiences in later posts in this series. For now, I will merely say that, in each of these scenarios, I found myself stuck. I was able to work out what <em>I</em> believed to be right, and generally I had some chain of reasoning that justified my beliefs. But ultimately, the different opinions that my colleagues held, the different actions that they took, were &#40;in a sense&#41; just as legitimate as my own, because we had not established common norms. That is to say, in the absence of a well-formed ethic, I had to personally struggle to navigate ethical situations, and I in many cases lacked the social structures necessary to challenge and alter what I viewed as others&#39; unethical behavior.</p>
<p>Now, I&#39;m an incoming Assistant Professor. Soon, the CoReACTER will have more students, more collaborations, and more projects. Soon, I&#39;ll be teaching undergraduates and graduate students&#33; I don&#39;t want to repeat the mistakes of my predecessors. I want to be an ethical scientist, and I want to create an environment for chemical research and teaching that is ethical and just.</p>
<p>So here I am, wandering through a dimly lit labyrinth, trying to find my way forward.</p>
<h2 id="scope">Scope</h2>
<p>Even preparing to write this zeroth post, I felt daunted. Developing a chemical ethic — that&#39;s a big ask&#33; To make this project more manageable &#40;and to set expectations&#41;, I find it helpful to establish the bounds of what I&#39;ll hope to cover in this series.</p>
<h3 id="the_chemical_sciences">The Chemical Sciences</h3>
<p>Throughout this piece so far, I&#39;ve used the phrase &quot;chemical science&quot;. It would perhaps be simpler to speak only of chemistry, but I can&#39;t do that. Chemistry is often called the &quot;central science&quot; in reference to its position between the physical sciences and the life sciences. The tendrils of chemistry reach far, from physics to agriculture. Though I consider myself a chemist, attend chemistry conferences, and typically publish my research in chemistry journals, my own background is highly interdisciplinary. My formal training is in materials science, but I&#39;ve worked in nanoparticle self-assembly &#40;applied physics&#41;, thermal fluids &#40;mechanical engineering&#41;, network science &#40;mathematics/computer science&#41;, and electrochemistry &#40;chemical engineering&#41;.</p>
<p>This series on &quot;chemical ethics&quot; will span the chemical sciences, by which I mainly mean chemistry, chemical engineering, and materials science, as well as their sub-disciplines. However, I will not hold myself to any strict disciplinary boundaries.</p>
<h3 id="chemical_ethics">Chemical Ethics</h3>
<p>What are chemical ethics? This is a question that I intend to explore in more depth in future posts &#40;see &quot;What&#39;s Next?&quot; below&#41;, but a preliminary definition and scoping cannot be avoided anymore.</p>
<p>Chemical ethics is an area of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Applied_ethics">applied ethics</a> and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Professional_ethics">professional ethics</a>. The study of chemical ethics involves determining appropriate approaches to moral questions related to the practice of chemistry and other chemical sciences. This includes activities related to academic and industrial chemical research, other industrial activities &#40;<em>e.g.</em>, managing a chemical plant or managing municipal chemical waste&#41;, and the professional interactions between chemical scientists and their broader communities and environments.</p>
<p>While I believe that chemical ethics is an underdeveloped area of study, my exploration will not be beginning from nothing. We can leverage the central position of chemistry as a discipline to gather useful ideas. In addition to bioethics, engineering ethics provides a valuable jumping-off point for analyses of chemical ethics; as the name implies, the ethics of chemical engineering at least partially fall within the domain of engineering ethics.</p>
<h2 id="why_not_just_science_ethics">Why Not Just Science Ethics?</h2>
<p>It&#39;s a fair question. While chemistry does have unique ethical dimensions, from synthesizing novel compounds to creating and remediating environmental pollution, much of the ethical questions in the chemical sciences can be more-or-less easily extended to other areas of scientific research or engineering. Couldn&#39;t this series just be <em>Foundations of Science Ethics</em> or <em>Foundations of Engineering Ethics</em>?</p>
<p>Sure it could&#33; But that&#39;s not what I&#39;m interested in, for a couple of reasons. First, as I&#39;ve already mentioned, non-chemical areas of research ethics and engineering ethics are already well-researched, robust fields of study. While I&#39;m sure I could make some meaningful contribution to these more general discussions, I see much less of a need for me to step into bioethics or engineering ethics. Second, where possible, I don&#39;t want to speak from a place of ignorance. This series will already involve me wading deep into areas outside of my expertise. It&#39;ll be much more manageable to think about and discuss ethics when applied to problems that I am already familiar with as a primarily academic chemical scientist with some exposure to industrial chemistry. Finally and most importantly, it doesn&#39;t need to be either-or. I can &#40;and probably will&#33;&#41; write about topics that are not exlusive to chemistry. Perhaps these posts could be labeled under &quot;research ethics&quot; or &quot;science ethics&quot; or &quot;engineering ethics&quot;, but they will still be relevant to chemical ethics and thus appropriate for this series.</p>
<h2 id="goals">Goals</h2>
<p>As I just alluded to, I am not a philosopher of science &#40;not yet, at least&#41;, and I have little philosophical or ethical training of any kind. While I believe that my interest in chemical ethics is important and worth pursuing, I know that my ideas are not yet mature. The <em>Foundations of Chemical Ethics</em> series is my attempt to learn by doing. Before I write any journal articles or manifestos, I&#39;ll be using this space to work through different ethical questions and &#40;hopefully&#41; get some feedback from my community.</p>
<p>My lofty goal is to develop a modern chemical ethic that goes beyond the somewhat vague and empty statements of existing ethical codes of conduct and perhaps even beyond the standards in fields like engineering, to provide a guide for chemical scientists trying to use their work to remedy the mistakes of the past and prevent future disasters. Climate change and sustainability will feature heavily in this ethic, as will various forms of social &#40;in&#41;justice.</p>
<p>More concretely, I hope to contribute some scholarly work on the topic of chemical ethics, either alone or in collaboration within the CoReACTER. I also hope to build up enough interesting and useful ideas to develop an ethics course for undergraduate and graduate chemical engineering students at Carnegie Mellon University.</p>
<h2 id="whats_next">What&#39;s Next?</h2>
<p>The next post in this series &#40;the actual first one&#41; will target a big question: &quot;What Is Chemistry For?&quot; I want to unpack the goals of the chemical sciences and chemical scientists. If we find that these goals aren&#39;t in line with some basic principles &#40;<em>e.g.</em>, justice&#41;, then we have a problem: we can&#39;t ethically justify chemical science in and of itself, and this whole exercise is moot. Barring that unfortunate situation, once we know the goals of the chemical sciences and what/who is meant to benefit from them, we can then focus our attention on figuring out how one can achieve those goals ethically.</p>
<p>Another important post will cover the idea of &quot;The Pillars of Chemical Research&quot;. Analogous to how biomedical research on human subjects has the ethical guiding lights of respect for persons, beneficence, and justice, I want to try and identify core ethical principles for chemical scientific research. Like &quot;What Is Chemistry For?&quot;, this post will serve as an important touchstone for future explorations.</p>
<p>Beyond those two posts, I don&#39;t know exactly where I&#39;ll go in this series. Some questions that I&#39;ve been thinking about, in no particular order:</p>
<ul>
<li><p>What is the ethical distance between &quot;pure&quot; chemists &#40;theoretical or experimental&#41; and &quot;applied&quot; chemists? How is this distance established, and what responsibilities do pure chemists have to prevent their ideas from causing harm?</p>
</li>
<li><p>On a similar note: do industrial chemical scientists have different ethical obligations to their academic counterparts?</p>
</li>
<li><p>Under what conditions is it ethical to labor in a context &#40;<em>e.g.</em>, an fossil fuel company&#41; that one knows or believes to be reducing human, non-human animal, or environmental wellbeing?</p>
</li>
<li><p>To what extent should chemical research or other labor in the chemical sciences be automated?</p>
</li>
<li><p>Is it ever ethical to use large language models or other &quot;AI&quot; tools in the chemical sciences? If so, what are the users&#39; obligations?</p>
</li>
<li><p>What ethical responsibilities do chemical scientists today hold for the wrongdoing and mistakes of past chemical scientists?</p>
</li>
<li><p>How should chemical standards and references be designed? What are the dangers of standards?</p>
</li>
<li><p>To what extent and under what conditions is it ethical for a chemical scientist to study problems that do not address significant societal problems?</p>
</li>
<li><p>What role should competition, prestige, and glory have in &#40;chemical&#41; science, particularly in the research setting? Is competition compatible with the goals of &#40;chemical&#41; science?</p>
</li>
<li><p>What are the standards for chemical harm? Can disclosing a molecule, material, or reaction be a form of harm in and of itself? What is &quot;due diligence&quot; in the context of chemical science; that is, when has a chemical scientist done enough to ensure that their work will cause as little harm as possible or will bring about as much benefit as possible? Is it ethical to make a &quot;bad&quot; process or compound &#40;<em>e.g.</em>, the extremely energy-intensive Haber-Bosch process&#41; more efficacious/less harmful, or is it only moral to design alternatives that are not harmful?</p>
</li>
<li><p>Chemists often speculate, for instance about mechanisms and spectral interpretation. Does speculation have any role in the chemical literature? If so, how should such speculation be communicated?</p>
</li>
</ul>
<h1 id="footnotes">Footnotes</h1>
<p><table class="fndef" id="fndef:1">
    <tr>
        <td class="fndef-backref">[1]</td>
        <td class="fndef-content"><a href="https://doi.org/10.2105/AJPH.2007.111930">DOI: 10.2105/AJPH.2007.111930</a></td>
    </tr>
</table>
 <table class="fndef" id="fndef:2">
    <tr>
        <td class="fndef-backref">[2]</td>
        <td class="fndef-content"><a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.etap.2008.03.003">DOI: 10.1016/j.etap.2008.03.003</a></td>
    </tr>
</table>
 <table class="fndef" id="fndef:3">
    <tr>
        <td class="fndef-backref">[3]</td>
        <td class="fndef-content"><a href="https://doi.org/10.1093/ije/dyl038">DOI: 10.1093/ije/dyl038</a></td>
    </tr>
</table>
 <table class="fndef" id="fndef:4">
    <tr>
        <td class="fndef-backref">[4]</td>
        <td class="fndef-content"><a href="https://doi.org/10.1002/bdrc.21096">DOI: 10.1002/bdrc.21096</a></td>
    </tr>
</table>
 <table class="fndef" id="fndef:5">
    <tr>
        <td class="fndef-backref">[5]</td>
        <td class="fndef-content"><a href="https://doi.org/10.1186/s12940-017-0340-3">DOI: 10.1186/s12940-017-0340-3</a></td>
    </tr>
</table>
 <table class="fndef" id="fndef:6">
    <tr>
        <td class="fndef-backref">[6]</td>
        <td class="fndef-content"><a href="https://doi.org/10.33263/BRIAC132.126">DOI: 10.33263/BRIAC132.126</a></td>
    </tr>
</table>
 <table class="fndef" id="fndef:7">
    <tr>
        <td class="fndef-backref">[7]</td>
        <td class="fndef-content"><a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.scitotenv.2019.134455">DOI: 10.1016/j.scitotenv.2019.134455</a></td>
    </tr>
</table>
 <table class="fndef" id="fndef:8">
    <tr>
        <td class="fndef-backref">[8]</td>
        <td class="fndef-content"><a href="https://doi.org/10.1002/9781119768432.ch12">DOI: 10.1002/9781119768432.ch12</a></td>
    </tr>
</table>
 <table class="fndef" id="fndef:9">
    <tr>
        <td class="fndef-backref">[9]</td>
        <td class="fndef-content"><a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.chemosphere.2023.138207">DOI: 10.1016/j.chemosphere.2023.138207</a></td>
    </tr>
</table>
 <table class="fndef" id="fndef:10">
    <tr>
        <td class="fndef-backref">[10]</td>
        <td class="fndef-content"><a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41370-018-0094-1">DOI: 10.1038/s41370-018-0094-1</a></td>
    </tr>
</table>
 <table class="fndef" id="fndef:11">
    <tr>
        <td class="fndef-backref">[11]</td>
        <td class="fndef-content"><a href="https://doi.org/10.1017/9781009157926.004">DOI: 10.1017/9781009157926.004</a></td>
    </tr>
</table>
 <table class="fndef" id="fndef:12">
    <tr>
        <td class="fndef-backref">[12]</td>
        <td class="fndef-content">Hippocrates is best known for the &quot;Hippocratic Oath&quot;, a commitment still sworn in some form by many doctors today, but he wrote extensively about the practice and philosophy of medicine.</td>
    </tr>
</table>
 <table class="fndef" id="fndef:13">
    <tr>
        <td class="fndef-backref">[13]</td>
        <td class="fndef-content">Though Jahr was the first to use the term &quot;bioethics&quot;, his ideas did not become popular. It was Van Rensselaer Potter, who re-invented the concept during the Cold War, who led to the development and widespread adoptions of bioethical ideas. See, <em>e.g.</em>, <a href="https://doi.org/10.1080/11287462.2015.1007616">DOI: 10.1080/11287462.2015.1007616</a>.</td>
    </tr>
</table>
 <table class="fndef" id="fndef:14">
    <tr>
        <td class="fndef-backref">[14]</td>
        <td class="fndef-content"><a href="https://doi.org/10.1353/ken.2008.0006">DOI: 10.1353/ken.2008.0006</a></td>
    </tr>
</table>
 <table class="fndef" id="fndef:15">
    <tr>
        <td class="fndef-backref">[15]</td>
        <td class="fndef-content"><a href="https://doi.org/10.1056/NEJM199711133372006">DOI: 10.1056/NEJM199711133372006</a></td>
    </tr>
</table>
 <table class="fndef" id="fndef:16">
    <tr>
        <td class="fndef-backref">[16]</td>
        <td class="fndef-content"><a href="https://www.acs.org/careers/career-services/ethics/the-chemical-professionals-code-of-conduct.html">https://www.acs.org/careers/career-services/ethics/the-chemical-professionals-code-of-conduct.html</a></td>
    </tr>
</table>
 <table class="fndef" id="fndef:17">
    <tr>
        <td class="fndef-backref">[17]</td>
        <td class="fndef-content"><a href="https://www.aiche.org/about/governance/policies/code-ethics">https://www.aiche.org/about/governance/policies/code-ethics</a></td>
    </tr>
</table>
 <table class="fndef" id="fndef:18">
    <tr>
        <td class="fndef-backref">[18]</td>
        <td class="fndef-content"><a href="https://www.rsc.org/globalassets/03-membership-community/join-us/membership-regulations/rsc-code-of-conduct-final.pdf">https://www.rsc.org/globalassets/03-membership-community/join-us/membership-regulations/rsc-code-of-conduct-final.pdf</a></td>
    </tr>
</table>
 <table class="fndef" id="fndef:19">
    <tr>
        <td class="fndef-backref">[19]</td>
        <td class="fndef-content"><a href="https://en.gdch.de/gdch/about-us/statutes-and-code-of-conduct.html">https://en.gdch.de/gdch/about-us/statutes-and-code-of-conduct.html</a></td>
    </tr>
</table>
 <table class="fndef" id="fndef:20">
    <tr>
        <td class="fndef-backref">[20]</td>
        <td class="fndef-content">The only journals that I&#39;m aware of that are squarely focused on any philosophy of chemistry are <em>Hyle: International Journal for Philosophy of Chemistry</em>, which ceased publishing in 2021, and <em>Foundations of Chemistry</em>.</td>
    </tr>
</table>
 <table class="fndef" id="fndef:21">
    <tr>
        <td class="fndef-backref">[21]</td>
        <td class="fndef-content"><em>Chemistry: The Impure Science</em> by Bernadette Bensaude-Vincent and Jonathan Simon &#40;2008&#41;</td>
    </tr>
</table>
 <table class="fndef" id="fndef:22">
    <tr>
        <td class="fndef-backref">[22]</td>
        <td class="fndef-content"><em>The Ethical Chemist</em> by Jeffrey Kovac &#40;2018&#41;</td>
    </tr>
</table>
 <table class="fndef" id="fndef:23">
    <tr>
        <td class="fndef-backref">[23]</td>
        <td class="fndef-content"><em>Good Chemistry: Methodological, Ethical, and Social Dimensions</em> by Jan Mehlich &#40;2021&#41;</td>
    </tr>
</table>
 <table class="fndef" id="fndef:24">
    <tr>
        <td class="fndef-backref">[24]</td>
        <td class="fndef-content"><em>Ethics of Chemistry: From Poison Gas to Climate Engineering</em>, edited by Joachim Schummer and Tom Børsen &#40;2021&#41;</td>
    </tr>
</table>
</p>
 ]]>
  </content:encoded>
    
  <pubDate>Mon, 06 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>  
  
  
  <atom:author>
    <atom:name>The CoReACTER; Evan Walter Clark Spotte-Smith</atom:name>
  </atom:author>
        
</item>

<item>
  <title>
    <![CDATA[  Funding  ]]>
  </title>
  <link> https://coreacter.org/funding/index.html </link>
  <guid> https://coreacter.org/funding/index.html </guid>
  <description>
    <![CDATA[  A description of funding in the CoReACTER. Where does our money come from? Who do we accept funding from, and why? What funding opportunities are we looking for?  ]]>
  </description>  
  
  <content:encoded>
    <![CDATA[  
<h1 id="funding">Funding</h1>
<h2 id="our_approach_to_funding">Our Approach to Funding</h2>
<p>The CoReACTER needs to maintain sufficient funding to continue operation. The funding process is morally fraught, and there are very few options for sustainable research funding that do not require some kind of ethical compromise. Understanding this, we are generally open to any funding source, though we try to move towards funding sources that are as aligned with our <a href="https://coreacter.org/philosophy/principles">principles</a> as possible.</p>
<p>There are, however, some areas that we will not consider because they are radically opposed to our principles, the good of the scientific community, and/or the wellbeing of society. The CoReACTER will not pursue or accept funding or other resources:</p>
<ul>
<li><p>From military sources &#40;<em>e.g.</em>, the United States Department of Defense&#41;, organizations whose major product or service relates to military technologies &#40;<em>i.e.</em>, members of the military-industrial complex&#41;, or from projects with direct military applications</p>
</li>
<li><p>For projects that will further the extraction and utilization of fossil fuels, or that otherwise are likely to significantly increase greenhouse gas emissions and/or accelerate anthropogenic climate change</p>
</li>
<li><p>That impede us from sharing our finding freely and openly, or that limit our ability to effectively collaborate</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p>We note that &quot;other resources&quot; includes computational resources. This means that we will not, for instance, pursue access to or access supercomputers owned and operated by the Department of Defense.</p>
<h2 id="current_funding_sources">Current Funding Sources</h2>
<table class="projectstab">
<colgroup>
<col width="30%" />
<col width="70%" />
</colgroup>
<thead></thead>
<tbody>	<tr>
		<td>
			<div class="project_logo"><img src="https://coreacter.org/_files/images/ucd_logo.png" class="project_logo" alt="The seal of University College Dublin. On a blue and green shield, from top to bottom, are three castles - each topped by flames; the words 'UCD Dublin'; and a gold harp"></div>
		</td>
		<td>
			<p><strong>Ad Astra Fellow Startup Funding</strong>, <em>University College Dublin</em> (2025–2030)<br>
			<strong>Project</strong>: TO BE DETERMINED<br>
			<strong>Description</strong>: Check back soon!</p>
		</td>
	</tr>
	<tr>
		<td>
			<div class="project_logo"><img src="https://coreacter.org/_files/images/trisarc.jpg" class="project_logo" alt="A promotional image for the TRI SARC. The name "Synthesis Advanced Research Challenge" is spelled in white in front of a black background. Below it is the Toyota Research Institute logo, consisting of the organization name and three triangles in red, gray, and white."></div>
		</td>
		<td>
			<p><strong>Synthesis Advanced Research Challenge</strong>, <em>Toyota Research Institute</em> (2024–2026)<br>
			<strong>Project</strong>: Direct Introduction of Competition and Kinetics to Materials Mechanism and Reaction Network Prediction<br>
			<strong>Description</strong>: Solid-state synthesis continues to be driven by trial-and-error experimentation, with no coherent design rules or underlying theory. Though there has been considerable interest in predicting the outcomes of solid-state reactions and automating the selection of precursors and synthesis conditions, most approaches developed to date rely entirely on bulk thermodynamics, ignoring the kinetics of nucleation and growth. Our proposed work provides a new approach for predictive materials synthesis, combining machine learning, molecular dynamics simulations, and chemical reaction networks to calculate solid-state reaction kinetics, rationally explain synthesis outcomes, and select precursors that are likely to lead to efficient formation of desired product phases.
</p>
		</td>
	</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<h2 id="previous_funding_sources">Previous Funding Sources</h2>
<table class="projectstab">
<colgroup>
<col width="40%" />
<col width="60%" />
</colgroup>
<thead></thead>
<tbody></tbody>
</table>
<h1 id="other_support">Other Support</h1>
<h2 id="computing_resources">Computing Resources</h2>
<table class="projectstab">
<colgroup>
<col width="30%" />
<col width="70%" />
</colgroup>
<thead></thead>
<tbody>	<tr>
		<td>
			<div class="project_logo"><img src="https://coreacter.org/_files/images/cmu_logo.png" class="project_logo" alt="The logo of Carnegie Mellon University, consisting of the words "Carnegie Mellon University" in white on a red square background."></div>
		</td>
		<td>
			<p><strong>Tartan Advanced Research Supercomputing Environment</strong>, <em>Carnegie Mellon University</em></p>
		</td>
	</tr>
	<tr>
		<td>
			<div class="project_logo"><img src="https://coreacter.org/_files/images/nsf_access_logo.png" class="project_logo" alt="The logo of the NSF (a globe with the letters "NSF" imposed on a 16-pointed wheel) next to the ACCESS logo (a stylized blue, orange, and white arrow pointing up and to the right, next to the word "ACCESS")"></div>
		</td>
		<td>
			<p><strong>Advanced Cyberinfrastructure Coordination Ecosystem Services & Support (ACCESS)</strong>, <em>US National Science Foundation (NSF)</em></p>
		</td>
	</tr>
	<tr>
		<td>
			<div class="project_logo"><img src="https://coreacter.org/_files/images/nairr_logo.png" class="project_logo" alt="A blue rectangle with the words "NAIRR Pilot" and, smaller and to the right, "National Artificial Intelligence Research Resource Pilot""></div>
		</td>
		<td>
			<p><strong>National Artificial Intelligence Research Resource (NAIRR) Pilot</strong>, <em>NSF and partners</em></p>
		</td>
	</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<h2 id="software">Software</h2>
<table class="projectstab">
<colgroup>
<col width="30%" />
<col width="70%" />
</colgroup>
<thead></thead>
<tbody>	<tr>
		<td>
			<div class="project_logo"><img src="https://coreacter.org/_files/images/zulip.png" class="project_logo" alt="The Zulip logo. A stylized white "z" sits in the middle of a blue-purple circle."></div>
		</td>
		<td>
			<p><strong>Zulip</strong><br>
			<strong>Description</strong>: Zulip is an organized team chat app designed for efficient communication. The CoReACTER is sponsored as an educational non-profit organization.</p>
		</td>
	</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
 ]]>
  </content:encoded>
    
  <pubDate>Mon, 07 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>  
  
  
  <atom:author>
    <atom:name>The CoReACTER; Evan Walter Clark Spotte-Smith</atom:name>
  </atom:author>
        
</item>

<item>
  <title>
    <![CDATA[  CoReACTER  ]]>
  </title>
  <link> https://coreacter.org/index.html </link>
  <guid> https://coreacter.org/index.html </guid>
  <description>
    <![CDATA[  The CoReACTER home page. We&#39;re a research organization based in the <a href="https://www.ucd.ie/chem/">School of Chemistry</a> at University College Dublin &#40;UCD&#41; and connected to the <a href="https://www.cheme.engineering.cmu.edu/index.html">Department of Chemical Engineering</a> of Carnegie Mellon University &#40;CMU&#41;.  ]]>
  </description>  
  
  <content:encoded>
    <![CDATA[  
<h1 id="welcome_to_the_coreacter">Welcome to the CoReACTER</h1>
<p>The <strong>Community of Researchers Assessing Chemical Transformations and Exploring Reactivity &#40;CoReACTER&#41;</strong> is a research organization that is based in the <a href="https://www.ucd.ie/chem/">School of Chemistry</a> at University College Dublin &#40;UCD&#41;; we also have ties with the <a href="https://www.cheme.engineering.cmu.edu/index.html">Department of Chemical Engineering</a> at Carnegie Mellon University &#40;CMU&#41;. We focus on leveraging developments in <strong>computational chemistry, chemical data science, and high-throughput experimentation</strong> to advance sustainable technologies in areas such as <strong>energy storage, chemical manufacturing, and waste management</strong>. You can learn more about our research efforts <a href="https://coreacter.org/research/">here</a> or look at our <a href="https://coreacter.org/publications/">publications</a>. </p>
<p>The CoReACTER is working hard to practice science in an <strong>ethical, thoughtful, and anti-oppressive</strong> fashion. This is an ongoing process, but you can read about our current thoughts and practices <a href="https://coreacter.org/philosophy/principles">here</a>. Our <a href="https://coreacter.org/resources/">resources</a> are mainly designed for <a href="https://coreacter.org/people/">ReACTERs</a> and other folks currently working and conducting research at CMU &#40;UCD-specific resources are coming&#33;&#41;, but you may also find these helpful&#33;</p>
<h1 id="land_acknowledgment">Land Acknowledgment</h1>
<p>We acknowledge that CMU occupies the unceded lands of the Seneca &#40;Haudenosaunee&#41;, Adena, Hopewell, Monongahela, Delaware, Shawnee, Mingo, and Lenape peoples, in what is now known as Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania in the United States of America. We recognize that we benefit from this unjust occupation, the colonization of this region, and the concomitant displacement and elimination of Native peoples. We strive to enter into respectful relationships with the peoples of these lands and with the lands themselves as we search for avenues for healing, justice, and reconciliation.</p>
<h1 id="news">News</h1>
<table class="newstab" style="border:0;">
<colgroup>
<col width="20%" />
<col width="80%" />
</colgroup>
<thead></thead>
<tbody>	<tr>
		<td>
			<em>Jun 2, 2025</em>
		</td>
		<td>
			<p>Vanshika Raj Singh is joining the CoReACTER this summer from BIT Mesra in India!
</p>
		</td>
	</tr>
	<tr>
		<td>
			<em>May 29, 2025</em>
		</td>
		<td>
			<p>EWCSS will be moving to Dublin, Ireland to begin an appointment as an Ad Astra Fellow at University College Dublin. They will retain an adjunct position at CMU, and the CoReACTER will continue to collaborate with CMU students and faculty. For more details, see <a href="https://coreacter.org/posts/20250530_leaving_before_the_beginning">our recent blog post</a>.
</p>
		</td>
	</tr>
	<tr>
		<td>
			<em>Sep 4, 2024</em>
		</td>
		<td>
			<p><a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/d41586-024-02838-z">EWCSS was interviewed in an article about intellectual property and large language models.</a>
</p>
		</td>
	</tr>
	<tr>
		<td>
			<em>Sep 1, 2024</em>
		</td>
		<td>
			<p><a href="https://www.linkedin.com/posts/toyota-research-institute_synthesis-challenge-proposal-winners-activity-7236734746406350848-DYON">EWCSS and Prof. Rachel Kurchin of CMU's Materials Science and Engineering department were selected to participate in the Toyota Research Institute Synthesis Advanced Research Challenge!</a>
</p>
		</td>
	</tr>
	<tr>
		<td>
			<em>Jun 3, 2024</em>
		</td>
		<td>
			<p><a href="https://www.cheme.engineering.cmu.edu/news/2024/06/03-spotte-smith-joins-faculty.html">EWCSS is going to join the CMU Chemical Engineering faculty as an Assistant Professor in 2025!</a></p>
		</td>
	</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
 ]]>
  </content:encoded>
    
  <pubDate>Mon, 23 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>  
  
  
  <atom:author>
    <atom:name>The CoReACTER; Evan Walter Clark Spotte-Smith</atom:name>
  </atom:author>
        
</item>

<item>
  <title>
    <![CDATA[  CoReACTER Philosophy: Principles  ]]>
  </title>
  <link> https://coreacter.org/philosophy/principles/index.html </link>
  <guid> https://coreacter.org/philosophy/principles/index.html </guid>
  <description>
    <![CDATA[  A description of the core principles guiding the work of the CoReACTER, and a brief overview of our broader philosophies. Note that our ideas and methods are evolving, and so this document should be considered a snapshot, rather than a static ideology.  ]]>
  </description>  
  
  <content:encoded>
    <![CDATA[  
<nav class="philosophy_nav">
  <ul>
    <li class="philosophy_nav"><a href="https://coreacter.org/philosophy/principles/">CoReACTER Principles</a></li>
    <li class="philosophy_nav"><a href="https://coreacter.org/philosophy/guidelines/">Guidelines for ReACTERs</a></li>
    <li class="philosophy_nav"><a href="https://coreacter.org/philosophy/openscience/">Open Science</a></li>
    <li class="philosophy_nav"><a href="https://coreacter.org/philosophy/decisionmaking/">Decision-Making in the CoReACTER</a></li>
  </ul>
  <img src="https://coreacter.org/assets/menudots.svg" id="philosophy-menu-icon" alt="Icon for philosophy page menu: three black dots in a circle" width="100">
</nav>
  
<h1 id="principles">Principles</h1>
<p><strong>All science is political</strong>. From the questions that we ask and the approaches that we take to answer them to the relationships that we build and the ways that we &#40;and others&#33;&#41; use science to make decisions, we are engaging in politics and driving political processes at various scales. Rather than try to ignore the role of politics in our scientific praxis, we are intentional and thoughtful about our political positionality.</p>
<p>The CoReACTER is an anti-oppressive research organization, aiming to subvert practices that are harmful and/or destructive to the well-being of ourselves, other humans, non-human life, and the planet. In particular, we align ourselves with:</p>
<ul>
<li><p>&#40;Intersectional&#41; feminism</p>
</li>
<li><p>Disability justice</p>
</li>
<li><p>Environmental justice and sustainability</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p>and we actively oppose the forces of:</p>
<ul>
<li><p>White supremacy, anti-Blackness, and racism</p>
</li>
<li><p>&#40;Cis&#41;sexism, homophobia, and transphobia</p>
</li>
<li><p>Capitalism and classism</p>
</li>
<li><p>Colonialism</p>
</li>
<li><p>Ableism</p>
</li>
<li><p>Nationalism&#40;s&#41; of all forms</p>
</li>
<li><p>Fascism and totalitarianism</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p>Academia is a deeply flawed system that is embedded in other flawed and harmful systems. Becuase of this, we cannot completely avoid engaging in Capitalism &#40;modern research universities operate as capitalistic enterprises; we also need to finance our research&#41;, colonialism &#40;CMU&#39;s campus is on stolen land, within a colonized country and colonizing nation-state&#41;, and nationalism &#40;most research is publicly funded, and publicly funded research generally supports national interests&#41;; perhaps this is also true of some of the other evils that we have outlined. Nonetheless, we openly challenge and subvert oppressive paradigms and structures where and how we can.</p>
<p>Our core principles, which guide us as we practice science, are:</p>
<ul>
<li><p><strong>Honesty</strong>: We are honest with ourselves, with our fellow ReACTERs, with the scientific community, and with the world. Honesty means truth-telling – saying what we know or believe to be right, whether it is convenient or not. It also means transparency. We strive to communicate openly throughout the scientific process, to share early and often rather than hoarding or hiding information.</p>
</li>
<li><p><strong>Humility</strong>: Often, &quot;humble&quot; is used to mean that one has a low opinion of one&#39;s self. Rather, when we say that we aim to be humble, we mean that we aim to avoid both excessive pride and self-deprecation. Through careful reflection and honest dialogue, we try to maintain an accurate, moderate understanding of ourselves, our knowledge, our behavior, and our place in our communities. Critical to effective humility is knowing our own limits, knowing what we know and what we don&#39;t know&#33;</p>
</li>
<li><p><strong>Collectivism</strong>: No scientist is an island. We are all part of many communities – groups of friends, colleagues, biological and found families, neighborhoods, folks who go to the same hair salon. Our approach to our work centers these communities, rather than our own interests. We are motivated to use scientific inquiry and our expertise to make our communities and the broader world better than we found them. Our work seeks to uplift others, particularly those in need. We will never harm or put down others for our personal benefit.</p>
</li>
<li><p><strong>Justice</strong>: Historically, Western science has been practiced primarily by the elite members of society. This elite practice has created or supported &#40;and continues, in many ways, to create and support&#41; regimes of oppression, repression, subjugation, and exclusion. While CoReACTER operates within traditional academic structures, we aim to push against oppressive practices and create more just policies and outcomes, within the Academy and outside of it.</p>
</li>
<li><p><strong>Kindness</strong>: In a world of competition, we choose collaboration. In a world of selfishness, we choose to give freely. In a world that is hard and unforgiving, we choose softness. Where we find ourselves given the choice, we choose to be kind: to ourselves, to each other, and to those around us. We aim to be empathetic and understand the perspectives of others, and where we cannot empathize, we sympathize and listen. </p>
</li>
<li><p><strong>Curiosity</strong>: Science as a philosophy offers tools for problem-solving, and we employ these tools to address meaningful problems, from fundamental theoretical questions to global challenges like anthropogenic climate change and plastic pollution. However, we refuse to treat science only as a means to a practical end. Rather, we center the joy of inquiry and celebrate discovery as an end in and of itself. As we do our work, we seek to learn and to facilitate the learning of others.</p>
</li>
</ul>
 ]]>
  </content:encoded>
    
  <pubDate>Sun, 14 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>  
  
  
  <atom:author>
    <atom:name>The CoReACTER; Evan Walter Clark Spotte-Smith</atom:name>
  </atom:author>
        
</item>

<item>
  <title>
    <![CDATA[  Research  ]]>
  </title>
  <link> https://coreacter.org/research/index.html </link>
  <guid> https://coreacter.org/research/index.html </guid>
  <description>
    <![CDATA[  A description of the research that happens in and around the CoReACTER. We focus primarily on computational and data chemistry, supplemented and supported by &#40;mostly high-throughput&#41; experiments. We work on method development, but our efforts are generally focused on applications related to sustainability. Currently, we are thinking about battery energy storage, electrocatalysis, and plastic waste management.  ]]>
  </description>  
  
  <content:encoded>
    <![CDATA[  
<h1 id="research">Research</h1>
<div class="franklin-toc"><ol><li>Chemical Data and Software</li><li>Data Science for Reactivity</li><li>Understanding Materials Synthesis</li><li>Electrochemical Transformations</li><li>Managing the Plastic Waste Crisis</li></ol></div>
<h2 id="chemical_data_and_software">Chemical Data and Software</h2>
<p>We develop and contribute to a range of datasets and software packages, providing new tools for the community to use to address diverse chemical problems.</p>
<p>To maximize utility, we focus on making our datasets FAIR &#40;<em>i.e.</em>, findable, accessible, interoperable, and reusable&#41;. To date, our data generation efforts have been focused on computational data generated using methods such as high-throughput density functional theory &#40;see EWCSS&#39; work on the <a href="https://doi.org/10.1039/D3DD00153A">Materials Project</a>&#41;. However, we are interested in developing experimental datasets as well, for instance leveraging the <a href="https://cloudlab.cmu.edu/">CMU Cloud Lab</a>.</p>
<p>In line with our commitment to <a href="https://coreacter.org/philosophy/openscience.md">open science</a>, we ensure that all of the data that we produce and contribute to is freely available to the community, and we only contribute to open source software projects.</p>
<h2 id="data_science_for_reactivity">Data Science for Reactivity</h2>
<p>The CoReACTER is broadly interested in explorations of chemical transformations. We see many opportunities to leverage machine learning &#40;ML&#41; and data science to make our studies faster and more efficient, and to allow us to obtain insights that would be impossible using conventional methods.</p>
<p>Machine learning interatomic potentials &#40;MLIPs&#41; are ML models that are trained to predict the energies of molecules and materials given their elemental species and atomic positions. We are currently investigating ways to apply MLIPs to automatically discover reaction mechanisms. We are also working to develop new MLIPs that are more flexible and better suited for complex reactive chemistry. In particular, we are interested in strategies to incorporate spin and charge information in MLIPs so that they can differentiate between systems at different spin and charge states.</p>
<p>High-throughput experimentation &#40;HTE&#41;, combined with ML-based optimization, provides another powerful opportunity to discover new reactions and optimize product yields. HTE, either using lab-scale liquid handlers or full-scale autonomous lab systems, offers a means to rapidly explore chemical space. However, even with high-throughput methods, it is often difficult or impossible to thoroughly search the domain of interest, making methods to effectively select promising experiments crucial. </p>
<h2 id="understanding_materials_synthesis">Understanding Materials Synthesis</h2>
<p>Materials synthesis is a field driven by empiricism and lacking in predictive theory or well-founded design rules. Trial-and-error experiments are expensive and time-consuming and are unlikely to yield optimal synthesis recipes. And while recent years have introduced a range of computational approaches to predict synthesizability and suggest precursors for synthesizing stable and metastable target phases, they have to date been limited by a near-exclusive focus on bulk thermodynamics, ignoring such important aspects as mass transport, kinetics, surface and grain boundary effects, defects, and the synthesis environment.</p>
<p>Our approach is to leverage molecular dynamics &#40;MD&#41; using MLIPs to simulate solid-state reactions, thereby allowing for the direct prediction of transport and reaction kinetics while accounting for a range of complicating variables &#40;e.g., impurities, defects, crystallographic orientations, fluid environments, etc.&#41;. This dynamics-based method will allow us to explain observed synthesis outcomes, including the presence of impurity phases and the order of phase emergence. Combining this approach with bulk thermodynamics calculations and CRNs, we can also improve materials retrosynthesis, predicting which precursors and reaction conditions will produce target phases with high purity and low energy and time input.</p>
<h2 id="electrochemical_transformations">Electrochemical Transformations</h2>
<p>Electrochemistry is well poised to help us reduce greenhouse gas emissions and mitigate the disastrous effects of anthropogenic climate change. Battery energy storage is replacing internal-combustion engines in vehicles and is helping to store excess solar and wind energy in the power grid, while electrocatalysis could potentially replace traditional thermochemical synthesis routes to feedstock chemicals and value-added products.</p>
<p>Unfortunately, electrochemical reactions are in general less well understood than thermochemical organic reactions, and as a result, progress towards next-generation energy-dense batteries and efficient electrosyntheses is slow. We believe that CRNs informed by first-principles simulations can change this and drive electrification forwards. We use CRNs to identify reaction mechanisms and understand what is going on in complex environments, such as the solid electrolyte interphase &#40;SEI&#41; in metal-ion batteries. By comparing the outcomes of different simulations, we can also leverage CRNs as an electrochemical design tool.</p>
<p>To get an even deeper understanding of complex electrochemical phenomena, we also turn towards multi-scale modeling. Generally, this involves using first-principles thermochemistry and kinetics to inform mesoscale &#40;<em>e.g.</em> kinetic Monte Carlo&#41; and continuum-scale models that can access experimentally relevant time scales and connect with key device-level observables.</p>
<h2 id="managing_the_plastic_waste_crisis">Managing the Plastic Waste Crisis</h2>
<p>Currently, humans produce about 200 million tons of plastic waste every year. That plastic takes up space in landfills, damages fragile ecosystems, and harms human and non-human health. We&#39;re interested in making plastics more sustainable. We are working to design catalysts that can convert common polymers like polyethylene and polypropylene into valuable chemicals, providing an economically viable route to eliminate waste from landfills. We&#39;re also interested in designing new polymers that can easily be chemically or biochemically decomposed&#33;</p>
<p>To tackle these challenges, we&#39;re most interested in leveraging HTE and ML. We may supplement our experimental studies with mechanistic studies using quantum chemical and dynamical simulations.</p>
 ]]>
  </content:encoded>
    
  <pubDate>Sun, 16 Jun 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>  
  
  
  <atom:author>
    <atom:name>The CoReACTER; Evan Walter Clark Spotte-Smith</atom:name>
  </atom:author>
        
</item>

<item>
  <title>
    <![CDATA[  CoReACTER Software  ]]>
  </title>
  <link> https://coreacter.org/software/index.html </link>
  <guid> https://coreacter.org/software/index.html </guid>
  <description>
    <![CDATA[  Software developed and/or maintained by the CoReACTER.  ]]>
  </description>  
  
  <content:encoded>
    <![CDATA[  
<h1 id="software">Software</h1>
<p>The CoReACTER develops software as part of our scholarly work&#33; All code is open source &#40;currently hosted on <a href="https://github.com/CoReACTER">GitHub</a>&#41;, in line with our commitment to <a href="https://coreacter.org/philosophy/openscience.md">open science</a>. Contributions from external developers are always welcome; please feel free to report issues and submit pull requests&#33;</p>
<p>Here, we list only packages that were initially or are primarily developed by the CoReACTER. However, we note that ReACTERs contribute to many other community codes&#33;</p>
<table class="softwaretab">
<colgroup>
<col width="30%" />
<col width="70%" />
</colgroup>
<thead></thead>
<tbody>	<tr>
		<td>
			<div class="project_logo"><img src="https://coreacter.org/_files/images/simpdirhypergraphs.png" class="project_logo" alt="The SimpleDirectedHypergraphs.jl logo. The package name is written in a sans-serif font. Above the text is a directed hypergraph, with arrows (directed hyperedges) connecting circles (vertices). Two of the circles replace the dots in the package name's "i"s."></div>
		</td>
		<td>
			<p><strong><a href="https://github.com/coreacter/SimpleDirectedHypergraphs.jl">SimpleDirectedHypergraphs.jl</a></strong><br>
<strong>Lead Developer</strong>: Evan Walter Clark Spotte-Smith (EWCSS) (they/them)<br>
<strong>Lead Maintainer</strong>: Evan Walter Clark Spotte-Smith (EWCSS) (they/them)
<br>
			<strong>Description</strong>: SimpleDirectedHypergraphs.jl is a Julia package for directed hypergraph data structures. It builds off of <a href="https://github.com/pszufe/SimpleHypergraphs.jl">SimpleHypergraphs.jl</a>, which in turn implements the <a href="https://juliagraphs.org/Graphs.jl/stable/core_functions/interface/">Graphs.jl interface</a>.</p>
		</td>
	</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
 ]]>
  </content:encoded>
    
  <pubDate>Thu, 13 Jun 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>  
  
  
  <atom:author>
    <atom:name>The CoReACTER; Evan Walter Clark Spotte-Smith</atom:name>
  </atom:author>
        
</item>

<item>
  <title>
    <![CDATA[  CoReACTER Data  ]]>
  </title>
  <link> https://coreacter.org/data/index.html </link>
  <guid> https://coreacter.org/data/index.html </guid>
  <description>
    <![CDATA[  Datasets and databases developed and/or maintained by the CoReACTER.  ]]>
  </description>  
  
  <content:encoded>
    <![CDATA[  
<h1 id="datasets">Datasets</h1>
 ]]>
  </content:encoded>
    
  <pubDate>Thu, 13 Jun 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>  
  
  
  <atom:author>
    <atom:name>The CoReACTER; Evan Walter Clark Spotte-Smith</atom:name>
  </atom:author>
        
</item>

<item>
  <title>
    <![CDATA[  Open Science and the CoReACTER  ]]>
  </title>
  <link> https://coreacter.org/philosophy/openscience/index.html </link>
  <guid> https://coreacter.org/philosophy/openscience/index.html </guid>
  <description>
    <![CDATA[  The open science philosophy of the CoReACTER.  ]]>
  </description>  
  
  <content:encoded>
    <![CDATA[  
<nav class="philosophy_nav">
  <ul>
    <li class="philosophy_nav"><a href="https://coreacter.org/philosophy/principles/">CoReACTER Principles</a></li>
    <li class="philosophy_nav"><a href="https://coreacter.org/philosophy/guidelines/">Guidelines for ReACTERs</a></li>
    <li class="philosophy_nav"><a href="https://coreacter.org/philosophy/openscience/">Open Science</a></li>
    <li class="philosophy_nav"><a href="https://coreacter.org/philosophy/decisionmaking/">Decision-Making in the CoReACTER</a></li>
  </ul>
  <img src="https://coreacter.org/assets/menudots.svg" id="philosophy-menu-icon" alt="Icon for philosophy page menu: three black dots in a circle" width="100">
</nav>
  
<h1 id="open_science">Open Science</h1>
<p>The CoReACTER is dedicated to open science, but what does that actually mean? &quot;Open science&quot; is a broad and vague term which means different things to different folks.<sup id="fnref:1">[1]</sup> For us, when we speak of &quot;open science&quot;, we mean that the practice of science should be transparent; that there should be minimal barriers to access the outputs of scholarly scientific work; and that science and research should be practiced within communities that extend beyond the boundaries of a research group, a university, or academia as a whole.</p>
<p>Here, we briefly describe some of our positions on open science and related practices. We emphasize that this page is meant only as an introduction to this discussion&#33;</p>
<h1 id="open_source_software">Open Source Software</h1>
<p>Much of our research involves developing scientific software. In addition to building and contributing to large-scale software projects, we frequently write code for data generation, analysis, and visualization. As such, open software is a significant part of our open science mission&#33;</p>
<p>We value open source software because it lowers the barrier to use and modify computational tools, potentially broadening the impact of our research efforts. Open source software can also lead to better, more correct code&#33; Because our software is transparent, other researchers and programmers can inspect, test, and modify the code that we write, potentially finding bugs and optimizations that we missed or adding new features that are beyond our capacity.</p>
<p>We commit to making all software developed by the CoReACTER available open-source. Currently, we use <a href="https://github.com/CoReACTER">GitHub</a> to host our software. We prefer restrictive licenses such as the <a href="https://opensource.org/license/gpl-3-0">GNU General Public License</a> that ensure that derivative software projects remain open-source, though we are willing to use more permissive licenses such as the <a href="https://opensource.org/license/mit">MIT license</a> or <a href="https://opensource.org/license/unlicense">The Unlicense</a>. We will only spend our time contributing to other software projects if they are open-source, and we try to use open-source codes for our research whenever possible.</p>
<h1 id="open_and_fair_data">Open &#40;and FAIR&#41; Data</h1>
<p>In the age of data science, data is power: power to discover patterns, power to create models, power to accelerate research, and more. As we are committed to mass empowerment, it is only fitting that we in the CoReACTER want to share data widely. Open data further improves the reproducibility of scientific research.</p>
<p>When we generate data that we believe may be valuable for future research, we publish that data openly under permissive <a href="https://creativecommons.org/">Creative Commons</a> licenses. But making data publicly available is only the first step. We understand that, to maximize the benefit that data can have on the scientific community, it should be <strong>FAIR</strong><sup id="fnref:2">[2]</sup> – <strong>f</strong>indable, <strong>a</strong>ccessible, <strong>i</strong>nteroperable, and <strong>r</strong>eusable. To this end, we develop and contribute to public data infrastructure, such as the <a href="https://materialsproject.org">Materials Project</a>, and we work with our collaborators around the world to make the data that we generate as useful and easy-to-use as possible.</p>
<h1 id="open_access">Open Access</h1>
<p>Many scientific publications are closed-access: institutions &#40;<em>e.g.</em>, libraries and universities&#41; or individual readers must pay for the privilege of reading. This slows the spread of information, particularly to those who lack resources and privilege. The CoReACTER strongly believes that science should serve the public good. As a consequence of this belief, we hold that published scientific outputs such as journal articles, book chapters, and whitepapers should be publicly available at no cost.</p>
<p>Before submitting to any journal, we commit to publishing our work as a preprint on servers such as <a href="arxiv.org">arXiv</a> and <a href="chemrxiv.org">ChemRxiv</a>. We strongly prefer open-access journals and will always submit to such venues when the CoReACTER is the primary or sole organization involved in a manuscript; we will also strongly advocate for open-access publications in all other cases. We further commit to making &#42;.PDF files of all CoReACTER publications available through this website.<sup id="fnref:3">[3]</sup></p>
<p>Noting the interest in open-access publications, many journals have begun charging authors to publish their work &#40;<em>via</em> so-called article processing charges or APCs&#41;, rather than charging readers. Under these schemes, including &quot;Gold Open Access&quot;, research becomes widely available, but with the consequence that only well-resourced researchers can afford to publish in many popular venues. Currently, the CoReACTER is willing to pay APCs to ensure that our publications are freely available. However, our priciples oppose this exploitative and unjust practice, and so we seek to minimize these payments. We specifically refuse to pay to publish in <em>Nature</em> and its family of journals, as they charge exorbitant fees &#40;greater than &#36;10,000 per article&#41; that, in our view, constitute rent-seeking behavior.</p>
<h1 id="footnotes">Footnotes</h1>
<p><table class="fndef" id="fndef:1">
    <tr>
        <td class="fndef-backref">[1]</td>
        <td class="fndef-content"><a href="https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-319-00026-8_2">DOI: 10.1007/978-3-319-00026-8_2</a></td>
    </tr>
</table>
 <table class="fndef" id="fndef:2">
    <tr>
        <td class="fndef-backref">[2]</td>
        <td class="fndef-content"><a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/sdata.2016.18">DOI: 10.1038/sdata.2016.18</a></td>
    </tr>
</table>
 <table class="fndef" id="fndef:3">
    <tr>
        <td class="fndef-backref">[3]</td>
        <td class="fndef-content">PDFs aren&#39;t the most accessible, and we are open to alternatives that allow us to share our research with <em>everyone</em>. If you have ideas to improve accessibility, please reach out&#33;</td>
    </tr>
</table>
</p>
 ]]>
  </content:encoded>
    
  <pubDate>Thu, 13 Jun 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>  
  
  
  <atom:author>
    <atom:name>The CoReACTER; Evan Walter Clark Spotte-Smith</atom:name>
  </atom:author>
        
</item>

<item>
  <title>
    <![CDATA[  CoReACTER Publications  ]]>
  </title>
  <link> https://coreacter.org/publications/index.html </link>
  <guid> https://coreacter.org/publications/index.html </guid>
  <description>
    <![CDATA[  Scholarly works published by the CoReACTER. This page is updated regularly with any papers published by the CoReACTER as an organization. Note that not all papers with ReACTERs as authors will be included here. For a complete list of publications by EWCSS, you can check out <a href="https://espottesmith.github.io/publications">their website</a>.  ]]>
  </description>  
  
  <content:encoded>
    <![CDATA[  
<p>This page is regularly updated with any papers published by the CoReACTER as an organization. Note that not all papers with ReACTERs as authors will be included here, but only papers borne out of CoReACTER projects. For a complete list of publications by EWCSS, you can check out <a href="https://espottesmith.github.io/publications">their website</a>.</p>
<h1 id="bibliography">Bibliography</h1>
<p>Download all publications as <a href="https://coreacter.org/_files/bib/publications.bib">BibTeX</a>.</p>
<div class="bibsection">
	<div class="bibsectiontitle"><h2>Forthcoming</h2></div>		<div class="bibentry"> 2) <a href=https://coreacter.org/_files/papers/spottesmith_considering_ethics_2025.pdf><em>Considering the Ethics of Large Machine Learning Models in the Chemical Sciences</em></a>.
		Evan Walter Clark Spotte-Smith.
		<i>In Review</i>, 2025.				</div></div>
<div class="bibsection">
	<div class="bibsectiontitle"><h2>Preprints</h2></div>		<div class="bibentry"> 1) <a href=https://coreacter.org/_files/papers/levine_shuaibi_omol_2025.pdf><em>The Open Molecules 2025 (OMol25) Dataset, Evaluations, and Models</em></a>.
		Daniel S. Levine*, Muhammed Shuaibi*, Evan Walter Clark Spotte-Smith, Michael G. Taylor, Muhammad R. Hasyim, Kyle Michel, Ilyes Batatia, Gábor Csányi, Misko Dzamba, Peter Eastman, Nathan C. Frey, Xiang Fu, Vahe Gharakhanyan, Aditi S. Krishnapriyan, Joshua A. Rackers, Sanjeev Raja, Ammar Rizvi, Andrew S. Rosen, Zachary Ulissi, Santiago Vargas, C. Lawrence Zitnick, Samuel M. Blau, Brandon M. Wood.
		<i>arXiv</i>, 2025.				</div></div>
<div class="bibsection">
	<div class="bibsectiontitle"><h2>Peer-Reviewed</h2></div></div>
 ]]>
  </content:encoded>
    
  <pubDate>Thu, 13 Jun 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>  
  
  
  <atom:author>
    <atom:name>The CoReACTER; Evan Walter Clark Spotte-Smith</atom:name>
  </atom:author>
        
</item>

<item>
  <title>
    <![CDATA[  CoReACTER Blog  ]]>
  </title>
  <link> https://coreacter.org/blog/index.html </link>
  <guid> https://coreacter.org/blog/index.html </guid>
  <description>
    <![CDATA[  The blog of the CoReACTER. Here, ReACTERs will post discussions of scientific topics, tutorials, and philosophical musings. Posts have been vetted and approved by the CoReACTER collectively but do not necessarily reflect the opinions of all ReACTERs.  ]]>
  </description>  
  
  <content:encoded>
    <![CDATA[  
<h1 id="the_coreacter_blog">The CoReACTER Blog</h1>
<p>Communication is a critical aspect of our jobs. As practitioners of science and engineering, we are responsible for clearly communicating our findings to our scientific peers. We also value our role in sharing information with the public and the press, and in teaching and training junior researchers. This blog is part of our efforts to meet these responsibilities&#33;</p>
<p>Every post here has been written by ReACTERs, discussed in a CoReACTER group organizational meeting, and approved through a collective decision-making process. This does <strong><em>NOT</em></strong> mean that each post reflects the views of each individual ReACTER, and in general, only the authors of a post and the CoReACTER as an organization should be held responsible for the views espoused in a given post.</p>
<p>In general, we will not take down a post once it has been edited and approved, as we would not want to pretend that our mistakes had not happened. Exceptions would include if, for instance, we had posted information without appropriate permissions or consent. If we find that we have made incorrect or harmful statements, we reserve the right to edit posts &#40;clearly indicating where edits have been made and why they were made&#41;, and in serious cases we may make further posts apologizing for improper statements or explaining how our views have evolved. These guidelines are part of our practices of accountability.</p>
<h2 id="posts">Posts</h2>
<table class="blogtab" style="border:0;">
<colgroup>
<col width="40%" />
<col width="60%" />
</colgroup>
<thead></thead>
<tbody>	<tr>
		<td>
			<div class="blog_preview_image"><img src="https://coreacter.org/_files/images/20250530_leaving_before_the_beginning/leaving_cmu_ucd_toc.png" class="blog_preview_image" alt="The presidential seal of Carnegie Mellon University (a stylized gold thistle in front of a tartan background, with the words 'Carnegie Mellon University' and 'Pittsburgh Pennsylvania 1900' in a surrounding circle) and, to the right, the seal of University College Dublin (a blue and green shield with three castles - each topped by flames; the words 'UCD Dublin'; and a gold harp)."></div>
		</td>
		<td>
			<h2><a href="https://coreacter.org/posts/20250530_leaving_before_the_beginning">Leaving Before the Beginning</a></h2><br>
			<p><em>Evan Walter Clark Spotte-Smith (EWCSS) (they/them)</em><br>
			Posted on: May 30, 2025<br>
		In response to the rise of fascism in the United States, EWCSS is leaving for University College Dublin in Ireland. This post explains their motivations for leaving Pittsburgh and moving to Dublin, as well as what this move will mean for the CoReA...
			</p>
		</td>
	</tr>
	<tr>
		<td>
			<div class="blog_preview_image"><img src="https://coreacter.org/_files/images/20250428_on_the_properties_of_gender_spaces/gender_toc.png" class="blog_preview_image" alt="A 3D plot with axes labeled 'masculinity', 'femininity', and 'androgyny' and a rough, bumpy, but somewhat spherical shape plotted. A point is circled; an arrow and text reading 'You are here' indicate the circle. To the left of the plot are the transgender, nonbinary, and intersex pride flags, along with the words 'Enter the Gender Space'."></div>
		</td>
		<td>
			<h2><a href="https://coreacter.org/posts/20250428_on_the_properties_of_gender_spaces">On the Properties of Gender Spaces</a></h2><br>
			<p><em>Evan Walter Clark Spotte-Smith (EWCSS) (they/them)</em><br>
			Posted on: Apr 28, 2025<br>
		EWCSS attempts to construct a framework for gender based on the mathematical concept of space. Drawing from Eve Kosofsky Sedgwick, as well as other theorists such as Judith Butler, they consider how gender categories are constructed from our fluct...
			</p>
		</td>
	</tr>
	<tr>
		<td>
			<div class="blog_preview_image"><img src="https://coreacter.org/_files/images/20241204_ethics_0/ethics_0_toc.png" class="blog_preview_image" alt="Above a set of gray scales, the text \"Foundations of Chemical Ethics\" reads in black. Below the scales is the text \"0. Foundations of Foundations\". The scales are flanked by a number of symbols of chemical works, all in black and white: to the left, a gas mask, a trefoil nuclear radiation warning symbol, and a beaker; to the right, a factory with smoke billowing and a pair of pills."></div>
		</td>
		<td>
			<h2><a href="https://coreacter.org/posts/20241204_ethical_foundations_0">Foundations of Chemical Ethics: 0. Foundations of Foundations</a></h2><br>
			<p><em>Evan Walter Clark Spotte-Smith (EWCSS) (they/them)</em><br>
			Posted on: Jan 6, 2025<br>
		In this preview, EWCSS introduces a new series on ethics in the chemical sciences. They discuss their motivations for embarking on this journey, their intended scope and goals, and they raise some possible directions for future posts.
			</p>
		</td>
	</tr>
	<tr>
		<td>
			<div class="blog_preview_image"><img src="https://coreacter.org/_files/images/20241027_what_if_theyre_all_wrong/toc.png" class="blog_preview_image" alt="Two reaction mechanisms are shown using 3D renderings of molecules. In one, labeled \"fast\" with a sparkling pink heart emoji, lithium hexafluorophosphate or LiPF6 reacts with lithium carbonate to form a variety of species, including LiPO2F2 and CO2. In the other, labeled \"slow\" with a crying face emoji, lithium hexafluorophosphate reacts with water to form species like hydrogen fluoride and PF4OH. This image is based on the table of contents graphic of \"Elementary Decomposition Mechanisms of Lithium Hexafluorophosphate in Battery Electrolytes and Interphases\" by Evan Walter Clark Spotte-Smith, Thea Bee Petrocelli, et al., DOI: 10.1021/acsenergylett.2c02351."></div>
		</td>
		<td>
			<h2><a href="https://coreacter.org/posts/20241027_what_if_theyre_all_wrong">What If They're Wrong?</a></h2><br>
			<p><em>Evan Walter Clark Spotte-Smith (EWCSS) (they/them)</em><br>
			Posted on: Jan 6, 2025<br>
		Inspired by a blog post by the mathematician Igor Pak, EWCSS considers mechanisms (e.g., reaction mechanisms) as a form of chemical conjecture. Using a recent example involving electrolyte decomposition in lithium-ion batteries, they explore the p...
			</p>
		</td>
	</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
 ]]>
  </content:encoded>
    
  <pubDate>Thu, 13 Jun 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>  
  
  
  <atom:author>
    <atom:name>The CoReACTER; Evan Walter Clark Spotte-Smith</atom:name>
  </atom:author>
        
</item>

<item>
  <title>
    <![CDATA[  Decision-Making in the CoReACTER  ]]>
  </title>
  <link> https://coreacter.org/philosophy/decisionmaking/index.html </link>
  <guid> https://coreacter.org/philosophy/decisionmaking/index.html </guid>
  <description>
    <![CDATA[  General practices and guidelines for decision-making in the CoReACTER.  ]]>
  </description>  
  
  <content:encoded>
    <![CDATA[  
<nav class="philosophy_nav">
  <ul>
    <li class="philosophy_nav"><a href="https://coreacter.org/philosophy/principles/">CoReACTER Principles</a></li>
    <li class="philosophy_nav"><a href="https://coreacter.org/philosophy/guidelines/">Guidelines for ReACTERs</a></li>
    <li class="philosophy_nav"><a href="https://coreacter.org/philosophy/openscience/">Open Science</a></li>
    <li class="philosophy_nav"><a href="https://coreacter.org/philosophy/decisionmaking/">Decision-Making in the CoReACTER</a></li>
  </ul>
  <img src="https://coreacter.org/assets/menudots.svg" id="philosophy-menu-icon" alt="Icon for philosophy page menu: three black dots in a circle" width="100">
</nav>
  
<h1 id="decision-making">Decision-Making</h1>
<p>As an anti-oppressive research organization, the CoReACTER is dedicated to community-centered, collective, and equitable decision-making. Here, we outline procedures that help us to live up to our ideals and aspirations while making the best decisions possible.</p>
<ol>
<li><p><em>Decisions are made democratically.</em> No one ReACTER has a greater ability to direct CoReACTER business than any other; in general, each individual is given an equitable &#40;if not always equal&#41; opportunity to voice their opinions and to vote to decide on appropriate courses of action.<sup id="fnref:1">[1]</sup></p>
</li>
<li><p><em>Involve as many stakeholders as possible.</em> When making a decision, we consider who will be affected. If possible, we try to call those stakeholders and affected parties into our decision-making process; this could involve consulting with external parties ahead of a meeting or inviting external parties to a CoReACTER group organizational meeting, where they will have full rights of participation. If a decision will disproportionately affect some ReACTERs or stakeholders, we try to privilege those affected perspectives in our discussions.</p>
</li>
<li><p><em>Consensus is the goal.</em> Although we operate as a democracy, we are not aiming for simple majority rule. Ideally, we want to reach agreements that satisfy as many ReACTERs and other stakeholders as possible. This means that, in our arguments, we should try to win over <em>everyone</em>, and we should constantly be on the look-out for opportunities to compromise on our ideas &#40;though not on our ideals&#33;&#41;.</p>
</li>
<li><p><em>Until it comes time to decide, discuss and listen without judgment.</em> The beginning of the decision-making process is the time to freely share ideas. Even if you come into the discussion with strong opinions, do not put down other ideas or push your own ideas. Rather, listen and carefully consider each person&#39;s perspective. Once everyone has said their piece and all of the ideas are in the air, then we can start to discriminate between ideas and find what might be the best course of action.</p>
</li>
<li><p><em>Opinions are not only spoken.</em> Not everyone will always speak their mind openly. Some folks may be naturally less open about their feelings and opinions, and others may specifically be uncomfortable voicing an opinion on certain topics. Given these possibilities, it is imperative that we not treat a lack of dissent as consent. When making decisions, consider body language and facial expression. Consider who is and who is not talking. If everyone appears open and enthusiastic, that&#39;s a good sign that the discussion is on the right track. If not, there may be concerns or problems with the proposed plan that have not been discussed yet.</p>
</li>
<li><p><em>When possible, do not make decisions in haste.</em> Making good decisions takes time and thought&#33; If a decision can be reached easily without significant disagreement, then it&#39;s appropriate to seize the opportunity and finalize immediately. On the other hand, if folks are butting heads or if consensus feels far away, be willing to give the decision more time, or to step away and reconvene after everyone has had time to reflect and devise more creative solutions. Some decisions will truly be urgent and will not have the luxury of second &#40;or third, or fourth&#41; discussions, but don&#39;t create urgency if it isn&#39;t there&#33;</p>
</li>
<li><p><em>Be willing to iterate.</em> The CoReACTER might not get the decision right the first time. It can be tempting to commit to our decisions, to pick a path and not stray from it. We must resist this urge and, when necessary, reassess and revise our previous decisions. In doing so, we should consider who has been affected by our initial decision and how we can be accountable to them while potentially changing our own course of action.</p>
</li>
</ol>
<h1 id="footnotes">Footnotes</h1>
<table class="fndef" id="fndef:1">
    <tr>
        <td class="fndef-backref">[1]</td>
        <td class="fndef-content">EWCSS, as PI, is deemed personally, professionally, and in some respects legally responsible for the work that takes place in the CoReACTER. Because of this imbalance in power, risk, and responsibility, there may be circumstances where EWCSS must make a decision unilaterally, without reaching consensus with the rest of the CoReACTER. Even in these cases, they commit to communicating regarding these decisions as much as possible with the CoReACTER, and to holding space for disagreement and dissent.</td>
    </tr>
</table> ]]>
  </content:encoded>
    
  <pubDate>Thu, 13 Jun 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>  
  
  
  <atom:author>
    <atom:name>The CoReACTER; Evan Walter Clark Spotte-Smith</atom:name>
  </atom:author>
        
</item>

<item>
  <title>
    <![CDATA[  CoReACTER Resources  ]]>
  </title>
  <link> https://coreacter.org/resources/index.html </link>
  <guid> https://coreacter.org/resources/index.html </guid>
  <description>
    <![CDATA[  This page contains resources that are mainly designed for members of the CoReACTER community &#40;ReACTERs and collaborators&#41;. Some resources may also be helpful to others at CMU or to members of the broader chemical or scientific community.  ]]>
  </description>  
  
  <content:encoded>
    <![CDATA[  
<h1 id="resources">Resources</h1>
<p>Here, we list some resources that might be helpful for you in your educational and research career. These resources are aimed at members of the CoReACTER. Fittingly, many are specific to folks at CMU or in the Pittsburgh area. If you have an additional resource that might help us, please reach out to suggest it&#33;</p>
<h2 id="resources_for_reacters">Resources for ReACTERs</h2>
<ul>
<li><p><a href="https://coreacter.org/_files/The_CoReACTER_Manual.pdf">The CoReACTER Manual</a>: For all your CoReACTER philosophy/policy/practices/advice needs.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="resources_for_ucd_students">Resources for UCD Students</h2>
<p>Work in progress; check back here soon&#33;</p>
<h2 id="resources_for_cmu_students">Resources for CMU Students</h2>
<ul>
<li><p><a href="https://www.cmu.edu/disability-resources/">Office of Disability Resources</a>: For information about disability accommodations. </p>
</li>
<li><p><a href="https://www.cmu.edu/counseling/">Counseling and Psychological Services &#40;CaPS&#41;</a>: For short-term mental health care on campus. Check out the FAQ <a href="https://www.cmu.edu/counseling/about-us/faq.html">here</a>.</p>
</li>
<li><p><a href="https://www.cmu.edu/counseling/resources/index.html">Mental Health Resources</a>: These include general provider searches, as well as crisis resources and specialized resources for disordered eating, substance issues, LGBTQIA&#43; mental health, and survivors of sexual and physical violence. If you need immediate help, call 412-268-2922 &#40;CaPS&#41;, 988 &#40;behavior and mental health crisis services&#41;, or 911 &#40;medical emergency&#41;.</p>
</li>
<li><p><a href="https://www.cmu.edu/student-affairs/resources/legal-consultation.html">Legal consultation</a>: Every CMU student gets one free 20-minute legal consultation. Consider reaching out here first&#33;</p>
</li>
<li><p>Research experience and job resources:</p>
<ul>
<li><p><a href="https://science.osti.gov/wdts/suli">DOE Science Undergraduate Laboratory Internships &#40;SULI&#41;</a>: Paid internships for students to work at one of the US national laboratories. Summer and semester internships are available.</p>
</li>
<li><p><a href="https://new.nsf.gov/funding/initiatives/reu/search">NSF Research Experiences for Undergraduates &#40;REU&#41;</a>: Paid research program through NSF. There are REU sites all over the country, so look around and see if anything interests you&#33;</p>
</li>
<li><p><a href="https://www.cmu.edu/uro/academic-research/huray/index.html">CMU Highway to Undergraduate Research in the Academic Year &#40;HURAY&#41;</a>: HURAY fellows are paid to do research for one year during the semester. It&#39;s a great way to get involved in research while getting compensation to support yourself&#33;</p>
</li>
<li><p><a href="https://www.cmu.edu/career/">CMU Career &amp; Professional Development Center &#40;CPDC&#41;</a>: The CPDC can help you practice for interviews and provide career counseling, among other services.</p>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><p><a href="http://chegsa.cheme.cmu.edu/">CMU Chemical Engineering Graduate Student Association &#40;ChEGSA&#41;</a>: ChEGSA supports grad students in many ways, including hosting social and professional events.</p>
</li>
<li><p><a href="https://issuu.com/cmuengineering/docs/cheme-doctoral-student-handbook-2024-2025?fr&#61;sMmM1NzY1MTUzNzE">ChemE Graduate Student Handbook</a></p>
</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="resources_for_cmu_staff">Resources for CMU Staff</h2>
<ul>
<li><p><a href="https://www.cmu.edu/hr/work-life/accommodations/index.html">Accommodations for Faculty and Staff Members</a>: For staff disability accommodations.</p>
</li>
<li><p><a href="https://research.jhu.edu/rdt/funding-opportunities/postdoctoral/">Postdoctoral Funding Opportunities</a>: Johns Hopkins University regularly puts together a list of fellowships for postdocs. Many are focused on biomedical research, but it&#39;s worth looking at&#33;</p>
</li>
<li><p><a href="https://chemjobber.blogspot.com/">Chemjobber</a>: Chemjobber is dedicated to helping chemists find jobs and to understanding the chemical job market. His chemistry faculty job spreadsheet is particularly useful if you&#39;re looking for jobs in academia&#33;</p>
</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="resources_for_interested_students">Resources for Interested Students</h2>
<ul>
<li><p><a href="https://www.cheme.engineering.cmu.edu/education/graduate-programs/graduate-application.html">The CMU ChemE Graduate Application</a></p>
</li>
<li><p><a href="http://chegsa.cheme.cmu.edu/dei-application-assistance/">Graduate Application Mentoring Program</a>: A ChEGSA program pairing undergrads applying to CMU ChemE with current graduate students who can help them write strong applications.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="educational_resources">Educational Resources</h2>
<p>This section is a work in progress; come back soon to see more resources&#33;</p>
<h3 id="ethics_and_justice">Ethics and Justice</h3>
<h3 id="accessibility">Accessibility</h3>
<ul>
<li><p><a href="https://www.reactivities.org/slice/about-slice">SLICE</a>: Sign Language Incorporation in Chemistry Education.</p>
</li>
<li><p><a href="https://www.pnnl.gov/labsigns">LabSigns</a>: An effort from Pacific Northwest National Laboratory to develop American Sign Language signs for STEM &#40;currently focused on environmental science&#41;</p>
</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="electrochemistry">Electrochemistry</h3>
<h3 id="catalysis">Catalysis</h3>
<h3 id="kinetics">Kinetics</h3>
<h3 id="programming_and_software_engineering">Programming and Software Engineering</h3>
<ul>
<li><p><a href="https://julialang.org/learning/">Resources for Learning Julia</a>: A series of guides to learn the Julia programming language, put together by the Julia folks themselves.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="data_science">Data Science</h3>
<ul>
<li><p><a href="https://themlbook.com/">The Hundred-Page Machine Learning Book</a>: A broad overview of machine learning by Andriy Burkov. The e-book version is pay-what-you-can, so this should be accessible to everyone&#33;</p>
</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="research_resources">Research Resources</h2>
<h3 id="conferences_and_workshops">Conferences and Workshops</h3>
<ul>
<li><p><a href="https://supersciencegrl.co.uk/conferences">Nessa the Chemist&#39;s Conference Database</a>: A curated list, mostly focused on organic and automation chemistry.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="research_tools">Research Tools</h3>
<ul>
<li><p><a href="https://openalex.org/">OpenAlex</a>: A powerful open source catalogue of scientific publications with an free API.</p>
</li>
<li><p><a href="https://www.connectedpapers.com/">Connected Papers</a>: An online tool for literature searching. Provide one paper &#40;<em>e.g.</em>, through a digital object identifier or DOI&#41; and see what related papers you might want to look at&#33;</p>
</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="equipment_and_techniques">Equipment and Techniques</h3>
<ul>
<li><p><a href="https://cloudlab.cmu.edu/">The CMU Cloud Lab</a>: Learn about the available equipment and get trained to use the software interface.</p>
</li>
<li><p><a href="https://cmu.edu/engineering/trace.html">Tartan Research Advanced Computing Environment &#40;TRACE&#41;</a>: Information on CMU Engineering&#39;s computer cluster.</p>
</li>
</ul>
 ]]>
  </content:encoded>
    
  <pubDate>Thu, 13 Jun 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>  
  
  
  <atom:author>
    <atom:name>The CoReACTER; Evan Walter Clark Spotte-Smith</atom:name>
  </atom:author>
        
</item>

<item>
  <title>
    <![CDATA[  CoReACTER Philosophy  ]]>
  </title>
  <link> https://coreacter.org/philosophy/guidelines/index.html </link>
  <guid> https://coreacter.org/philosophy/guidelines/index.html </guid>
  <description>
    <![CDATA[  General guidelines for members of the CoReACTER.  ]]>
  </description>  
  
  <content:encoded>
    <![CDATA[  
<nav class="philosophy_nav">
  <ul>
    <li class="philosophy_nav"><a href="https://coreacter.org/philosophy/principles/">CoReACTER Principles</a></li>
    <li class="philosophy_nav"><a href="https://coreacter.org/philosophy/guidelines/">Guidelines for ReACTERs</a></li>
    <li class="philosophy_nav"><a href="https://coreacter.org/philosophy/openscience/">Open Science</a></li>
    <li class="philosophy_nav"><a href="https://coreacter.org/philosophy/decisionmaking/">Decision-Making in the CoReACTER</a></li>
  </ul>
  <img src="https://coreacter.org/assets/menudots.svg" id="philosophy-menu-icon" alt="Icon for philosophy page menu: three black dots in a circle" width="100">
</nav>
  
<h1 id="guidelines_for_reacters">Guidelines for ReACTERs</h1>
<p>These are our guidelines, general practices that we try to remember as we go about our days in the office/computer/laboratory and away from it. While they are meant for <a href="https://coreacter.org/people/">ReACTERs</a>, perhaps others may find them helpful&#33;</p>
<ol>
<li><p><em>Communicate.</em> The saying goes that &quot;silence is golden&quot;, but in our experience, open communication is a lot nicer and helps a research organization run well. If you&#39;re having a problem &#40;technical, personal, or otherwise&#41;, ask for help&#33; If you see someone else struggling, ask them what&#39;s wrong or offer your support. Chat with your fellow ReACTERs to coordinate equipment usage and compute time, to brainstorm new ideas, and to work through conflicts. If you&#39;re in doubt as to whether communication is needed, err on the side of over-communication.</p>
</li>
<li><p><em>Set and respect boundaries.</em> If you let it, the worlds of Academia and scientific research will take everything from you – your time, your peace of mind, even your health. Boundaries are a way that we protect ourselves and look after our well-being. Early and often, consider what you need to be happy and healthy, and state those needs as boundaries. These boundaries could involve how you communicate and what you communicate about; when you do and do not engage with work; and much more. Hopefully, those around you will respect clearly communicated boundaries, but you may need to periodically re-assert them. You should feel free in doing so, as maintaining and protecting your boundaries is ultimately good for you and those around you. Likewise, if your colleagues tell you their boundaries, listen, make note of them, and &#40;assuming these boundaries are reasonable&#41; take care not to cross those boundaries. If you do violate them in some way, recognize that harm &#40;see below&#41;, apologize, try to repair, and work to improve so that you respect your colleagues better in the future.</p>
</li>
<li><p><em>Limit work time and take breaks.</em> In the CoReACTER, productivity is not our ultimate goal. We want to improve the practice of science and use science to better the world, but not at the expense of our own health and potential for joy. At the same time, we believe that time spent on research does not necessarily correlate with productivity. Rather, you will be a better scientist if you take time for rest, for personal relationships with friends, families, and loves, for hobbies, for fun, for absolutely nothing at all. We encourage ReACTERs to design sustainable patterns of labor that incorporate regular rest and relaxation. We also try to incorporate breaks into our rhythm as a group, with shared meals, games, informal discussions, retreats, and more.</p>
</li>
<li><p><em>Recognize and fix mistakes early.</em> We will make mistakes. That means you will make mistakes, too. Rather than waiting for problems to arise, double-check yourself early &#40;or ask a colleague to help look for mistakes&#33;&#41;, so that you can correct them before they blow up &#40;literally or figuratively&#41;. This advice applies to research projects – selecting parameters for calculations, designing experiments, performing analysis – and also to interpersonal interactions. Taking time to reflect and thinking about how you could have handled a situation better will help you to avoid tension and minimize the harm you do to others&#33;</p>
</li>
<li><p><em>Be on time.</em> Especially because we limit the time that we spend on work &#40;see above&#41;, our hours in the office and the lab are valuable. Being on time is a way to show care and respect for yourself and for those around you. If you are worried about running late, try to give yourself buffer time so that others don&#39;t need to wait for you. If you know that you&#39;re going to be late, communicate that as early as possible so that others can respond and plan accordingly. We understand that things happen, and we will always try to give grace &#40;especially acknowledging that relationships around time and punctuality are culturally dependent&#41;, but it&#39;s easier if you do your part&#33;</p>
</li>
<li><p><em>Show up to meetings.</em> We know, there are a lot of meetings, possibly too many. Where possible, we encourage you to structure your work to minimize the number of meetings that are on your plate. However, we strongly advise that you attend meetings that are essential for the CoReACTER &#40;group organizational and research meetings&#41; or for your specific project &#40;project team meetings, meetings with collaborators and funders&#41;. These meetings will help you to stay up to date on what your colleagues are working on and help you to get feedback on your work. In addition to being physically present, we ask you to show up by actively participating in the technical discussion as well as the social environment. If well designed, meetings can build relationships and community&#33;</p>
</li>
</ol>
 ]]>
  </content:encoded>
    
  <pubDate>Thu, 13 Jun 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>  
  
  
  <atom:author>
    <atom:name>The CoReACTER; Evan Walter Clark Spotte-Smith</atom:name>
  </atom:author>
        
</item>

<item>
  <title>
    <![CDATA[  Practices of Accountability  ]]>
  </title>
  <link> https://coreacter.org/philosophy/accountability/index.html </link>
  <guid> https://coreacter.org/philosophy/accountability/index.html </guid>
  <description>
    <![CDATA[  Practices of accountability employed in the CoReACTER.  ]]>
  </description>  
  
  <content:encoded>
    <![CDATA[  
<nav class="philosophy_nav">
  <ul>
    <li class="philosophy_nav"><a href="https://coreacter.org/philosophy/principles/">CoReACTER Principles</a></li>
    <li class="philosophy_nav"><a href="https://coreacter.org/philosophy/guidelines/">Guidelines for ReACTERs</a></li>
    <li class="philosophy_nav"><a href="https://coreacter.org/philosophy/openscience/">Open Science</a></li>
    <li class="philosophy_nav"><a href="https://coreacter.org/philosophy/decisionmaking/">Decision-Making in the CoReACTER</a></li>
  </ul>
  <img src="https://coreacter.org/assets/menudots.svg" id="philosophy-menu-icon" alt="Icon for philosophy page menu: three black dots in a circle" width="100">
</nav>
  
<h1 id="accountability">Accountability</h1>
<p>This page is a work in progress; come back soon for more details&#33;</p>
 ]]>
  </content:encoded>
    
  <pubDate>Thu, 13 Jun 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>  
  
  
  <atom:author>
    <atom:name>The CoReACTER; Evan Walter Clark Spotte-Smith</atom:name>
  </atom:author>
        
</item>
</channel></rss>