<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rss version="2.0"
  xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
  xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"
  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
  xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss">

  <channel>
    <title>
      <![CDATA[  The CoReACTER  ]]>
    </title>
    <link> https://coreacter.org </link>
    <description>
      <![CDATA[  Organization website for the Community of Researchers Assessing Chemical Transformations and Exploring Reactivity &#40;CoReACTER&#41;  ]]>
    </description>
    <atom:link
      href="https://coreacter.org/feed.xml"
      rel="self"
      type="application/rss+xml" />


<item>
  <title>
    <![CDATA[  CoReACTER  ]]>
  </title>
  <link> https://coreacter.org/index.html </link>
  <guid> https://coreacter.org/index.html </guid>
  <description>
    <![CDATA[  The CoReACTER home page. We&#39;re a research organization based in the <a href="https://www.ucd.ie/chem/">School of Chemistry</a> at University College Dublin &#40;UCD&#41; and connected to the <a href="https://www.cheme.engineering.cmu.edu/index.html">Department of Chemical Engineering</a> of Carnegie Mellon University &#40;CMU&#41;.  ]]>
  </description>  
  
  <content:encoded>
    <![CDATA[  
<h1 id="welcome_to_the_coreacter">Welcome to the CoReACTER</h1>
<p>The <strong>Community of Researchers Assessing Chemical Transformations and Exploring Reactivity &#40;CoReACTER&#41;</strong> is a research organization that is based in the <a href="https://www.ucd.ie/chem/">School of Chemistry</a> at University College Dublin &#40;UCD&#41; and has ties with the <a href="https://www.cheme.engineering.cmu.edu/index.html">Department of Chemical Engineering</a> at Carnegie Mellon University &#40;CMU&#41;. We focus on leveraging developments in <strong>computational chemistry, chemical data science, and high-throughput experimentation</strong> to advance sustainable technologies in areas such as <strong>energy storage, chemical manufacturing, and waste management</strong>. You can learn more about our research efforts <a href="https://coreacter.org/research/">here</a> or look at our <a href="https://coreacter.org/publications/">publications</a>. </p>
<p>The CoReACTER is working hard to practice science in an <strong>ethical, thoughtful, and anti-oppressive</strong> fashion. This is an ongoing process, but you can read about our current thoughts and practices <a href="https://coreacter.org/philosophy/principles">here</a>. Our <a href="https://coreacter.org/resources/">resources</a> are mainly designed for <a href="https://coreacter.org/people/">ReACTERs</a> and other folks currently working and conducting research at CMU &#40;UCD-specific resources are coming&#33;&#41;, but you may also find these helpful&#33;</p>
<h1 id="land_acknowledgment">Land Acknowledgment</h1>
<p>We acknowledge that CMU occupies the unceded lands of the Seneca &#40;Haudenosaunee&#41;, Adena, Hopewell, Monongahela, Delaware, Shawnee, Mingo, and Lenape peoples, in what is now known as Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania in the United States of America. We recognize that we benefit from this unjust occupation, the colonization of this region, and the concomitant displacement and elimination of Native peoples. We strive to enter into respectful relationships with the peoples of these lands and with the lands themselves as we search for avenues for healing, justice, and reconciliation.</p>
<h1 id="news">News</h1>
<table class="newstab" style="border:0;">
<colgroup>
<col width="20%" />
<col width="80%" />
</colgroup>
<thead></thead>
<tbody>	<tr>
		<td>
			<em>May 29, 2025</em>
		</td>
		<td>
			<p>EWCSS will be moving to Dublin, Ireland to begin an appointment as an Ad Astra Fellow at University College Dublin. They will retain an adjunct position at CMU, and the CoReACTER will continue to collaborate with CMU students and faculty. For more details, see <a href="https://coreacter.org/posts/20250530_leaving_before_the_beginning">our recent blog post</a>.
</p>
		</td>
	</tr>
	<tr>
		<td>
			<em>Sep 4, 2024</em>
		</td>
		<td>
			<p><a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/d41586-024-02838-z">EWCSS was interviewed in an article about intellectual property and large language models.</a>
</p>
		</td>
	</tr>
	<tr>
		<td>
			<em>Sep 1, 2024</em>
		</td>
		<td>
			<p><a href="https://www.linkedin.com/posts/toyota-research-institute_synthesis-challenge-proposal-winners-activity-7236734746406350848-DYON">EWCSS and Prof. Rachel Kurchin of CMU's Materials Science and Engineering department were selected to participate in the Toyota Research Institute Synthesis Advanced Research Challenge!</a>
</p>
		</td>
	</tr>
	<tr>
		<td>
			<em>Jun 3, 2024</em>
		</td>
		<td>
			<p><a href="https://www.cheme.engineering.cmu.edu/news/2024/06/03-spotte-smith-joins-faculty.html">EWCSS is going to join the CMU Chemical Engineering faculty as an Assistant Professor in 2025!</a></p>
		</td>
	</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
 ]]>
  </content:encoded>
    
  <pubDate>Mon, 23 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>  
  
  
  <atom:author>
    <atom:name>The CoReACTER; Evan Walter Clark Spotte-Smith</atom:name>
  </atom:author>
        
</item>

<item>
  <title>
    <![CDATA[  CoReACTER Resources  ]]>
  </title>
  <link> https://coreacter.org/resources/index.html </link>
  <guid> https://coreacter.org/resources/index.html </guid>
  <description>
    <![CDATA[  This page contains resources that are mainly designed for members of the CoReACTER community &#40;ReACTERs and collaborators&#41;. Some resources may also be helpful to others at CMU or to members of the broader chemical or scientific community.  ]]>
  </description>  
  
  <content:encoded>
    <![CDATA[  
<h1 id="resources">Resources</h1>
<p>Here, we list some resources that might be helpful for you in your educational and research career. These resources are aimed at members of the CoReACTER. Fittingly, many are specific to folks at CMU or in the Pittsburgh area. If you have an additional resource that might help us, please reach out to suggest it&#33;</p>
<h2 id="resources_for_reacters">Resources for ReACTERs</h2>
<ul>
<li><p><a href="https://coreacter.org/_files/The_CoReACTER_Manual.pdf">The CoReACTER Manual</a>: For all your CoReACTER philosophy/policy/practices/advice needs.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="resources_for_ucd_students">Resources for UCD Students</h2>
<p>Work in progress; check back here soon&#33;</p>
<h2 id="resources_for_cmu_students">Resources for CMU Students</h2>
<ul>
<li><p><a href="https://www.cmu.edu/disability-resources/">Office of Disability Resources</a>: For information about disability accommodations. </p>
</li>
<li><p><a href="https://www.cmu.edu/counseling/">Counseling and Psychological Services &#40;CaPS&#41;</a>: For short-term mental health care on campus. Check out the FAQ <a href="https://www.cmu.edu/counseling/about-us/faq.html">here</a>.</p>
</li>
<li><p><a href="https://www.cmu.edu/counseling/resources/index.html">Mental Health Resources</a>: These include general provider searches, as well as crisis resources and specialized resources for disordered eating, substance issues, LGBTQIA&#43; mental health, and survivors of sexual and physical violence. If you need immediate help, call 412-268-2922 &#40;CaPS&#41;, 988 &#40;behavior and mental health crisis services&#41;, or 911 &#40;medical emergency&#41;.</p>
</li>
<li><p><a href="https://www.cmu.edu/student-affairs/resources/legal-consultation.html">Legal consultation</a>: Every CMU student gets one free 20-minute legal consultation. Consider reaching out here first&#33;</p>
</li>
<li><p>Research experience and job resources:</p>
<ul>
<li><p><a href="https://science.osti.gov/wdts/suli">DOE Science Undergraduate Laboratory Internships &#40;SULI&#41;</a>: Paid internships for students to work at one of the US national laboratories. Summer and semester internships are available.</p>
</li>
<li><p><a href="https://new.nsf.gov/funding/initiatives/reu/search">NSF Research Experiences for Undergraduates &#40;REU&#41;</a>: Paid research program through NSF. There are REU sites all over the country, so look around and see if anything interests you&#33;</p>
</li>
<li><p><a href="https://www.cmu.edu/uro/academic-research/huray/index.html">CMU Highway to Undergraduate Research in the Academic Year &#40;HURAY&#41;</a>: HURAY fellows are paid to do research for one year during the semester. It&#39;s a great way to get involved in research while getting compensation to support yourself&#33;</p>
</li>
<li><p><a href="https://www.cmu.edu/career/">CMU Career &amp; Professional Development Center &#40;CPDC&#41;</a>: The CPDC can help you practice for interviews and provide career counseling, among other services.</p>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><p><a href="http://chegsa.cheme.cmu.edu/">CMU Chemical Engineering Graduate Student Association &#40;ChEGSA&#41;</a>: ChEGSA supports grad students in many ways, including hosting social and professional events.</p>
</li>
<li><p><a href="https://issuu.com/cmuengineering/docs/cheme-doctoral-student-handbook-2024-2025?fr&#61;sMmM1NzY1MTUzNzE">ChemE Graduate Student Handbook</a></p>
</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="resources_for_cmu_staff">Resources for CMU Staff</h2>
<ul>
<li><p><a href="https://www.cmu.edu/hr/work-life/accommodations/index.html">Accommodations for Faculty and Staff Members</a>: For staff disability accommodations.</p>
</li>
<li><p><a href="https://research.jhu.edu/rdt/funding-opportunities/postdoctoral/">Postdoctoral Funding Opportunities</a>: Johns Hopkins University regularly puts together a list of fellowships for postdocs. Many are focused on biomedical research, but it&#39;s worth looking at&#33;</p>
</li>
<li><p><a href="https://chemjobber.blogspot.com/">Chemjobber</a>: Chemjobber is dedicated to helping chemists find jobs and to understanding the chemical job market. His chemistry faculty job spreadsheet is particularly useful if you&#39;re looking for jobs in academia&#33;</p>
</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="resources_for_interested_students">Resources for Interested Students</h2>
<ul>
<li><p><a href="https://www.cheme.engineering.cmu.edu/education/graduate-programs/graduate-application.html">The CMU ChemE Graduate Application</a></p>
</li>
<li><p><a href="http://chegsa.cheme.cmu.edu/dei-application-assistance/">Graduate Application Mentoring Program</a>: A ChEGSA program pairing undergrads applying to CMU ChemE with current graduate students who can help them write strong applications.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="educational_resources">Educational Resources</h2>
<p>This section is a work in progress; come back soon to see more resources&#33;</p>
<h3 id="ethics_and_justice">Ethics and Justice</h3>
<h3 id="accessibility">Accessibility</h3>
<ul>
<li><p><a href="https://www.reactivities.org/slice/about-slice">SLICE</a>: Sign Language Incorporation in Chemistry Education.</p>
</li>
<li><p><a href="https://www.pnnl.gov/labsigns">LabSigns</a>: An effort from Pacific Northwest National Laboratory to develop American Sign Language signs for STEM &#40;currently focused on environmental science&#41;</p>
</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="electrochemistry">Electrochemistry</h3>
<h3 id="catalysis">Catalysis</h3>
<h3 id="kinetics">Kinetics</h3>
<h3 id="programming_and_software_engineering">Programming and Software Engineering</h3>
<ul>
<li><p><a href="https://julialang.org/learning/">Resources for Learning Julia</a>: A series of guides to learn the Julia programming language, put together by the Julia folks themselves.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="data_science">Data Science</h3>
<ul>
<li><p><a href="https://themlbook.com/">The Hundred-Page Machine Learning Book</a>: A broad overview of machine learning by Andriy Burkov. The e-book version is pay-what-you-can, so this should be accessible to everyone&#33;</p>
</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="research_resources">Research Resources</h2>
<h3 id="conferences_and_workshops">Conferences and Workshops</h3>
<ul>
<li><p><a href="https://supersciencegrl.co.uk/conferences">Nessa the Chemist&#39;s Conference Database</a>: A curated list, mostly focused on organic and automation chemistry.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="research_tools">Research Tools</h3>
<ul>
<li><p><a href="https://openalex.org/">OpenAlex</a>: A powerful open source catalogue of scientific publications with an free API.</p>
</li>
<li><p><a href="https://www.connectedpapers.com/">Connected Papers</a>: An online tool for literature searching. Provide one paper &#40;<em>e.g.</em>, through a digital object identifier or DOI&#41; and see what related papers you might want to look at&#33;</p>
</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="equipment_and_techniques">Equipment and Techniques</h3>
<ul>
<li><p><a href="https://cloudlab.cmu.edu/">The CMU Cloud Lab</a>: Learn about the available equipment and get trained to use the software interface.</p>
</li>
<li><p><a href="https://cmu.edu/engineering/trace.html">Tartan Research Advanced Computing Environment &#40;TRACE&#41;</a>: Information on CMU Engineering&#39;s computer cluster.</p>
</li>
</ul>
 ]]>
  </content:encoded>
    
  <pubDate>Thu, 13 Jun 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>  
  
  
  <atom:author>
    <atom:name>The CoReACTER; Evan Walter Clark Spotte-Smith</atom:name>
  </atom:author>
        
</item>
</channel></rss>