<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rss version="2.0"
  xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
  xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"
  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
  xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss">

  <channel>
    <title>
      <![CDATA[  The CoReACTER  ]]>
    </title>
    <link> https://coreacter.github.io </link>
    <description>
      <![CDATA[  Organization website for the Community of Researchers Assessing Chemical Transformations and Exploring Reactivity &#40;CoReACTER&#41;  ]]>
    </description>
    <atom:link
      href="https://coreacter.github.io/feed.xml"
      rel="self"
      type="application/rss+xml" />


<item>
  <title>
    <![CDATA[  CoReACTER Blog  ]]>
  </title>
  <link> https://coreacter.github.io/blog/index.html </link>
  <guid> https://coreacter.github.io/blog/index.html </guid>
  <description>
    <![CDATA[  The blog of the CoReACTER. Here, ReACTERs will post discussions of scientific topics, tutorials, and philosophical musings. All posts have been vetted and approved by the CoReACTER collectively but do not necessarily reflect the opinions of all ReACTERs.  ]]>
  </description>  
  
  <content:encoded>
    <![CDATA[  
<h1 id="the_coreacter_blog">The CoReACTER Blog</h1>
<p>Communication is a critical aspect of our jobs. As practitioners of science and engineering, we are responsible for clearly communicating our findings to our scientific peers. We also value our role in sharing information with the public and the press, and in teaching and training junior researchers. This blog is part of our efforts to meet these responsibilities&#33;</p>
<p>Every post here has been written by ReACTERs, discussed in a CoReACTER group organizational meeting, and approved through a collective decision-making process. This does <strong><em>NOT</em></strong> mean that each post reflects the views of each individual ReACTER, and in general, only the authors of a post and the CoReACTER as an organization should be held responsible for the views espoused in a given post.</p>
<p>In general, we will not take down a post once it has been edited and approved, as we would not want to pretend that our mistakes had not happened. Exceptions would include if, for instance, we had posted information without appropriate permissions or consent. If we find that we have made incorrect or harmful statements, we reserve the right to edit posts &#40;clearly indicating where edits have been made and why they were made&#41;, and in serious cases we may make further posts apologizing for improper statements or explaining how our views have evolved. These guidelines are part of our practices of accountability.</p>
<h2 id="posts">Posts</h2>
 ]]>
  </content:encoded>
    
  <pubDate>Thu, 13 Jun 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>  
  
  
  <atom:author>
    <atom:name>The CoReACTER; Evan Walter Clark Spotte-Smith</atom:name>
  </atom:author>
        
</item>
</channel></rss>