<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rss version="2.0"
  xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
  xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"
  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
  xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss">

  <channel>
    <title>
      <![CDATA[  The CoReACTER  ]]>
    </title>
    <link> https://coreacter.github.io </link>
    <description>
      <![CDATA[  Organization website for the Community of Researchers Assessing Chemical Transformations and Exploring Reactivity &#40;CoReACTER&#41;  ]]>
    </description>
    <atom:link
      href="https://coreacter.github.io/feed.xml"
      rel="self"
      type="application/rss+xml" />


<item>
  <title>
    <![CDATA[  CoReACTER  ]]>
  </title>
  <link> https://coreacter.github.io/index.html </link>
  <guid> https://coreacter.github.io/index.html </guid>
  <description>
    <![CDATA[  The CoReACTER home page. We&#39;re a research organization operating in the <a href="https://www.cheme.engineering.cmu.edu/index.html">Department of Chemical Engineering</a> of Carnegie Mellon University &#40;CMU&#41;.  ]]>
  </description>  
  
  <content:encoded>
    <![CDATA[  
<h1 id="welcome_to_the_coreacter">Welcome to the CoReACTER</h1>
<p>The <strong>Community of Researchers Assessing Chemical Transformations and Exploring Reactivity &#40;CoReACTER&#41;</strong> is a research organization that operates within the <a href="https://www.cheme.engineering.cmu.edu/index.html">Department of Chemical Engineering</a> at Carnegie Mellon University &#40;CMU&#41;. We focus on leveraging developments in <strong>computational chemistry, chemical data science, and high-throughput experimentation</strong> to advance sustainable technologies in areas such as <strong>energy storage, chemical manufacturing, and waste management</strong>. You can learn more about our research efforts <a href="https://coreacter.github.io/research/">here</a> or look at our <a href="https://coreacter.github.io/publications/">publications</a>. </p>
<p>The CoReACTER is working hard to practice science in an <strong>ethical, thoughtful, and anti-oppressive</strong> fashion. This is an ongoing process, but you can read about our current thoughts and practices <a href="https://coreacter.github.io/philosophy/principles">here</a>. Our <a href="https://coreacter.github.io/resources/">resources</a> are mainly designed for <a href="https://coreacter.github.io/people/">ReACTERs</a> and other folks currently working and conducting research at CMU, but you may also find these helpful&#33;</p>
<h1 id="land_acknowledgment">Land Acknowledgment</h1>
<p>We acknowledge that CMU occupies the unceded lands of the Seneca &#40;Haudenosaunee&#41;, Shawnee, and Lenape peoples, in what is now known as Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania in the United States of America. We recognize that we benefit from this unjust occupation, the colonization of this region, and the concomitant displacement and elimination of Native peoples. We strive to enter into respectful relationships with the peoples of these lands and with the lands themselves as we search for avenues for healing, justice, and reconciliation.</p>
<h1 id="news">News</h1>
<table class="newstab" style="border:0;">
<colgroup>
<col width="20%" />
<col width="80%" />
</colgroup>
<thead></thead>
<tbody>	<tr>
		<td>
			<em>Sep 4, 2024</em>
		</td>
		<td>
			<p><a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/d41586-024-02838-z">EWCSS was interviewed in an article about intellectual property and large language models.</a>
</p>
		</td>
	</tr>
	<tr>
		<td>
			<em>Sep 1, 2024</em>
		</td>
		<td>
			<p><a href="https://www.linkedin.com/posts/toyota-research-institute_synthesis-challenge-proposal-winners-activity-7236734746406350848-DYON">EWCSS and Prof. Rachel Kurchin of CMU's Materials Science and Engineering department were selected to participate in the Toyota Research Institute Synthesis Advanced Research Challenge!</a>
</p>
		</td>
	</tr>
	<tr>
		<td>
			<em>Jun 3, 2024</em>
		</td>
		<td>
			<p><a href="https://www.cheme.engineering.cmu.edu/news/2024/06/03-spotte-smith-joins-faculty.html">EWCSS is going to join the CMU Chemical Engineering faculty as an Assistant Professor in 2025!</a></p>
		</td>
	</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
 ]]>
  </content:encoded>
    
  <pubDate>Mon, 23 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>  
  
  
  <atom:author>
    <atom:name>The CoReACTER; Evan Walter Clark Spotte-Smith</atom:name>
  </atom:author>
        
</item>

<item>
  <title>
    <![CDATA[  CoReACTER Philosophy: Principles  ]]>
  </title>
  <link> https://coreacter.github.io/philosophy/principles/index.html </link>
  <guid> https://coreacter.github.io/philosophy/principles/index.html </guid>
  <description>
    <![CDATA[  A description of the core principles guiding the work of the CoReACTER, and a brief overview of our broader philosophies. Note that our ideas and methods are evolving, and so this document should be considered a snapshot, rather than a static ideology.  ]]>
  </description>  
  
  <content:encoded>
    <![CDATA[  
<nav class="philosophy_nav">
  <ul>
    <li class="philosophy_nav"><a href="https://coreacter.github.io/philosophy/principles/">CoReACTER Principles</a></li>
    <li class="philosophy_nav"><a href="https://coreacter.github.io/philosophy/guidelines/">Guidelines for ReACTERs</a></li>
    <li class="philosophy_nav"><a href="https://coreacter.github.io/philosophy/openscience/">Open Science</a></li>
    <li class="philosophy_nav"><a href="https://coreacter.github.io/philosophy/decisionmaking/">Decision-Making in the CoReACTER</a></li>
  </ul>
  <img src="https://coreacter.github.io/assets/menudots.svg" id="philosophy-menu-icon" alt="Icon for philosophy page menu: three black dots in a circle">
</nav>
  
<h1 id="principles">Principles</h1>
<p><strong>All science is political</strong>. From the questions that we ask and the approaches that we take to answer them to the relationships that we build and the ways that we &#40;and others&#33;&#41; use science to make decisions, we are engaging in politics and driving political processes at various scales. Rather than try to ignore the role of politics in our scientific praxis, we are intentional and thoughtful about our political positionality.</p>
<p>The CoReACTER is an anti-oppressive research organization, aiming to subvert practices that are harmful and/or destructive to the well-being of ourselves, other humans, non-human life, and the planet. In particular, we align ourselves with:</p>
<ul>
<li><p>&#40;Intersectional&#41; feminism</p>
</li>
<li><p>Disability justice</p>
</li>
<li><p>Environmental justice and sustainability</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p>and we actively oppose the forces of:</p>
<ul>
<li><p>White supremacy, anti-Blackness, and racism</p>
</li>
<li><p>&#40;Cis&#41;sexism, homophobia, and transphobia</p>
</li>
<li><p>Capitalism and classism</p>
</li>
<li><p>Colonialism</p>
</li>
<li><p>Ableism</p>
</li>
<li><p>Nationalism&#40;s&#41; of all forms</p>
</li>
<li><p>Fascism and totalitarianism</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p>Academia is a deeply flawed system that is embedded in other flawed and harmful systems. Becuase of this, we cannot completely avoid engaging in Capitalism &#40;modern research universities operate as capitalistic enterprises; we also need to finance our research&#41;, colonialism &#40;CMU&#39;s campus is on stolen land, within a colonized country and colonizing nation-state&#41;, and nationalism &#40;most research that takes place in the United States is publicly funded, and publicly funded research generally supports American national interests&#41;; perhaps this is also true of some of the other evils that we have outlined. Nonetheless, we openly challenge and subvert oppressive paradigms and structures where and how we can.</p>
<p>Our core principles, which guide us as we practice science, are:</p>
<ul>
<li><p><strong>Honesty</strong>: We are honest with ourselves, with our fellow ReACTERs, with the scientific community, and with the world. Honesty means truth-telling – saying what we know or believe to be right, whether it is convenient or not. It also means transparency. We strive to communicate openly throughout the scientific process, to share early and often rather than hoarding or hiding information.</p>
</li>
<li><p><strong>Humility</strong>: Often, &quot;humble&quot; is used to mean that one has a low opinion of one&#39;s self. Rather, when we say that we aim to be humble, we mean &#40;following LeGuin&#41; that we aim to avoid both excessive pride and self-deprecation. Through careful reflection and honest dialogue, we try to maintain an accurate, moderate understanding of ourselves, our knowledge, our behavior, and our place in our communities. Critical to effective humility is knowing our own limits, knowing what we know and what we don&#39;t know&#33;</p>
</li>
<li><p><strong>Collectivism</strong>: No scientist is an island. We are all part of many communities – groups of friends, colleagues, biological and found families, neighborhoods, folks who go to the same hair salon. Our approach to our work centers these communities, rather than our own interests. We are motivated to use scientific inquiry and our expertise to make our communities and the broader world better than we found them. Our work seeks to uplift others, particularly those in need. We will never harm or put down others for our personal benefit.</p>
</li>
<li><p><strong>Justice</strong>: Historically, Western science has been practiced primarily by the elite members of society. This elite practice has created or supported &#40;and continues, in many ways, to create and support&#41; regimes of oppression, repression, subjugation, and exclusion. While CoReACTER operates within traditional academic structures, we aim to push against oppressive practices and create more just policies and outcomes, within the Academy and outside of it.</p>
</li>
<li><p><strong>Kindness</strong>: In a world of competition, we choose collaboration. In a world of selfishness, we choose to give freely. In a world that is hard and unforgiving, we choose softness. Where we find ourselves given the choice, we choose to be kind: to ourselves, to each other, and to those around us. We aim to be empathetic and understand the perspectives of others, and where we cannot empathize, we sympathize and listen. </p>
</li>
<li><p><strong>Curiosity</strong>: Science as a philosophy offers tools for problem-solving, and we employ these tools to address meaningful problems, from fundamental theoretical questions to global challenges like anthropogenic climate change and plastic pollution. However, we refuse to treat science only as a means to a practical end. Rather, we center the joy of inquiry and celebrate discovery as an end in and of itself. As we do our work, we seek to learn and to facilitate the learning of others.</p>
</li>
</ul>
 ]]>
  </content:encoded>
    
  <pubDate>Sun, 14 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>  
  
  
  <atom:author>
    <atom:name>The CoReACTER; Evan Walter Clark Spotte-Smith</atom:name>
  </atom:author>
        
</item>

<item>
  <title>
    <![CDATA[  CoReACTER Software  ]]>
  </title>
  <link> https://coreacter.github.io/software/index.html </link>
  <guid> https://coreacter.github.io/software/index.html </guid>
  <description>
    <![CDATA[  Software developed and/or maintained by the CoReACTER.  ]]>
  </description>  
  
  <content:encoded>
    <![CDATA[  
<h1 id="software">Software</h1>
 ]]>
  </content:encoded>
    
  <pubDate>Thu, 13 Jun 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>  
  
  
  <atom:author>
    <atom:name>The CoReACTER; Evan Walter Clark Spotte-Smith</atom:name>
  </atom:author>
        
</item>

<item>
  <title>
    <![CDATA[  CoReACTER Data  ]]>
  </title>
  <link> https://coreacter.github.io/data/index.html </link>
  <guid> https://coreacter.github.io/data/index.html </guid>
  <description>
    <![CDATA[  Datasets and databases developed and/or maintained by the CoReACTER.  ]]>
  </description>  
  
  <content:encoded>
    <![CDATA[  
<h1 id="datasets">Datasets</h1>
 ]]>
  </content:encoded>
    
  <pubDate>Thu, 13 Jun 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>  
  
  
  <atom:author>
    <atom:name>The CoReACTER; Evan Walter Clark Spotte-Smith</atom:name>
  </atom:author>
        
</item>

<item>
  <title>
    <![CDATA[  CoReACTER Publications  ]]>
  </title>
  <link> https://coreacter.github.io/publications/index.html </link>
  <guid> https://coreacter.github.io/publications/index.html </guid>
  <description>
    <![CDATA[  Scholarly works published by the CoReACTER. This page is updated regularly with any papers published by the CoReACTER as an organization. Note that not all papers with ReACTERs as authors will be included here. For a complete list of publications by Prof. Spotte-Smith, you can check out <a href="https://espottesmith.github.io/publications">their website</a>.  ]]>
  </description>  
  
  <content:encoded>
    <![CDATA[  
<p>This page is regularly updated with any papers published by the CoReACTER as an organization. Note that not all papers with ReACTERs as authors will be included here, but only papers borne out of CoReACTER projects. For a complete list of publications by Dr. Spotte-Smith, you can check out <a href="https://espottesmith.github.io/publications">their website</a>.</p>
<p>Currently we have no publications out &#40;we&#39;re a very new organization&#33;&#41;, but check back soon.</p>
<h1 id="bibliography">Bibliography</h1>
<p>Download all publications as <a href="https://coreacter.github.io/_files/bib/publications.bib">BibTeX</a>.</p>
<div class="bibsection">
	<div class="bibsectiontitle"><h2>Forthcoming</h2></div></div>
<div class="bibsection">
	<div class="bibsectiontitle"><h2>Preprints</h2></div></div>
<div class="bibsection">
	<div class="bibsectiontitle"><h2>Peer-Reviewed</h2></div></div>
 ]]>
  </content:encoded>
    
  <pubDate>Thu, 13 Jun 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>  
  
  
  <atom:author>
    <atom:name>The CoReACTER; Evan Walter Clark Spotte-Smith</atom:name>
  </atom:author>
        
</item>

<item>
  <title>
    <![CDATA[  CoReACTER Blog  ]]>
  </title>
  <link> https://coreacter.github.io/blog/index.html </link>
  <guid> https://coreacter.github.io/blog/index.html </guid>
  <description>
    <![CDATA[  The blog of the CoReACTER. Here, ReACTERs will post discussions of scientific topics, tutorials, and philosophical musings. All posts have been vetted and approved by the CoReACTER collectively but do not necessarily reflect the opinions of all ReACTERs.  ]]>
  </description>  
  
  <content:encoded>
    <![CDATA[  
<h1 id="the_coreacter_blog">The CoReACTER Blog</h1>
<p>Communication is a critical aspect of our jobs. As practitioners of science and engineering, we are responsible for clearly communicating our findings to our scientific peers. We also value our role in sharing information with the public and the press, and in teaching and training junior researchers. This blog is part of our efforts to meet these responsibilities&#33;</p>
<p>Every post here has been written by ReACTERs, discussed in a CoReACTER group organizational meeting, and approved through a collective decision-making process. This does <strong><em>NOT</em></strong> mean that each post reflects the views of each individual ReACTER, and in general, only the authors of a post and the CoReACTER as an organization should be held responsible for the views espoused in a given post.</p>
<p>In general, we will not take down a post once it has been edited and approved, as we would not want to pretend that our mistakes had not happened. Exceptions would include if, for instance, we had posted information without appropriate permissions or consent. If we find that we have made incorrect or harmful statements, we reserve the right to edit posts &#40;clearly indicating where edits have been made and why they were made&#41;, and in serious cases we may make further posts apologizing for improper statements or explaining how our views have evolved. These guidelines are part of our practices of accountability.</p>
<h2 id="posts">Posts</h2>
 ]]>
  </content:encoded>
    
  <pubDate>Thu, 13 Jun 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>  
  
  
  <atom:author>
    <atom:name>The CoReACTER; Evan Walter Clark Spotte-Smith</atom:name>
  </atom:author>
        
</item>

<item>
  <title>
    <![CDATA[  CoReACTER Resources  ]]>
  </title>
  <link> https://coreacter.github.io/resources/index.html </link>
  <guid> https://coreacter.github.io/resources/index.html </guid>
  <description>
    <![CDATA[  This page contains resources that are mainly designed for members of the CoReACTER community &#40;ReACTERs and collaborators&#41;. Some resources may also be helpful to others at CMU or to members of the broader chemical or scientific community.  ]]>
  </description>  
  
  <content:encoded>
    <![CDATA[  
<h1 id="resources">Resources</h1>
<p>Here, we list some resources that might be helpful for you in your educational and research career. These resources are aimed at members of the CoReACTER. Fittingly, many are specific to folks at CMU or in the Pittsburgh area. If you have an additional resource that might help us, please reach out to suggest it&#33;</p>
<h2 id="resources_for_cmu_students">Resources for CMU Students</h2>
<ul>
<li><p><a href="https://www.cmu.edu/disability-resources/">Office of Disability Resources</a>: For information about disability accommodations. </p>
</li>
<li><p><a href="https://www.cmu.edu/counseling/">Counseling and Psychological Services &#40;CaPS&#41;</a>: For short-term mental health care on campus. Check out the FAQ <a href="https://www.cmu.edu/counseling/about-us/faq.html">here</a>.</p>
</li>
<li><p><a href="https://www.cmu.edu/counseling/resources/index.html">Mental Health Resources</a>: These include general provider searches, as well as crisis resources and specialized resources for disordered eating, substance issues, LGBTQIA&#43; mental health, and survivors of sexual and physical violence. If you need immediate help, call 412-268-2922 &#40;CaPS&#41;, 988 &#40;behavior and mental health crisis services&#41;, or 911 &#40;medical emergency&#41;.</p>
</li>
<li><p><a href="https://www.cmu.edu/student-affairs/resources/legal-consultation.html">Legal consultation</a>: Every CMU student gets one free 20-minute legal consultation. Consider reaching out here first&#33;</p>
</li>
<li><p>Research experience and job resources:</p>
<ul>
<li><p><a href="https://science.osti.gov/wdts/suli">DOE Science Undergraduate Laboratory Internships &#40;SULI&#41;</a>: Paid internships for students to work at one of the US national laboratories. Summer and semester internships are available.</p>
</li>
<li><p><a href="https://new.nsf.gov/funding/initiatives/reu/search">NSF Research Experiences for Undergraduates &#40;REU&#41;</a>: Paid research program through NSF. There are REU sites all over the country, so look around and see if anything interests you&#33;</p>
</li>
<li><p><a href="https://www.cmu.edu/uro/academic-research/huray/index.html">CMU Highway to Undergraduate Research in the Academic Year &#40;HURAY&#41;</a>: HURAY fellows are paid to do research for one year during the semester. It&#39;s a great way to get involved in research while getting compensation to support yourself&#33;</p>
</li>
<li><p><a href="https://www.cmu.edu/career/">CMU Career &amp; Professional Development Center &#40;CPDC&#41;</a>: The CPDC can help you practice for interviews and provide career counseling, among other services.</p>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><p><a href="http://chegsa.cheme.cmu.edu/">CMU Chemical Engineering Graduate Student Association &#40;ChEGSA&#41;</a>: ChEGSA supports grad students in many ways, including hosting social and professional events.</p>
</li>
<li><p><a href="https://issuu.com/cmuengineering/docs/cheme-doctoral-student-handbook-2024-2025?fr&#61;sMmM1NzY1MTUzNzE">ChemE Graduate Student Handbook</a></p>
</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="resources_for_cmu_staff">Resources for CMU Staff</h2>
<ul>
<li><p><a href="https://www.cmu.edu/hr/work-life/accommodations/index.html">Accommodations for Faculty and Staff Members</a>: For staff disability accommodations.</p>
</li>
<li><p><a href="https://research.jhu.edu/rdt/funding-opportunities/postdoctoral/">Postdoctoral Funding Opportunities</a>: Johns Hopkins University regularly puts together a list of fellowships for postdocs. Many are focused on biomedical research, but it&#39;s worth looking at&#33;</p>
</li>
<li><p><a href="https://chemjobber.blogspot.com/">Chemjobber</a>: Chemjobber is dedicated to helping chemists find jobs and to understanding the chemical job market. His chemistry faculty job spreadsheet is particularly useful if you&#39;re looking for jobs in academia&#33;</p>
</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="resources_for_interested_students">Resources for Interested Students</h2>
<ul>
<li><p><a href="https://www.cheme.engineering.cmu.edu/education/graduate-programs/graduate-application.html">The CMU ChemE Graduate Application</a></p>
</li>
<li><p><a href="http://chegsa.cheme.cmu.edu/dei-application-assistance/">Graduate Application Mentoring Program</a>: A ChEGSA program pairing undergrads applying to CMU ChemE with current graduate students who can help them write strong applications.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="educational_resources">Educational Resources</h2>
<p>This section is a work in progress; come back soon to see more resources&#33;</p>
<h3 id="ethics_and_justice">Ethics and Justice</h3>
<h3 id="electrochemistry">Electrochemistry</h3>
<h3 id="catalysis">Catalysis</h3>
<h3 id="kinetics">Kinetics</h3>
<h3 id="programming_and_software_engineering">Programming and Software Engineering</h3>
<ul>
<li><p><a href="https://julialang.org/learning/">Resources for Learning Julia</a>: A series of guides to learn the Julia programming language, put together by the Julia folks themselves.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="data_science">Data Science</h3>
<ul>
<li><p><a href="https://themlbook.com/">The Hundred-Page Machine Learning Book</a>: A broad overview of machine learning by Andriy Burkov. The e-book version is pay-what-you-can, so this should be accessible to everyone&#33;</p>
</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="research_resources">Research Resources</h2>
<h3 id="conferences_and_workshops">Conferences and Workshops</h3>
<ul>
<li><p><a href="https://supersciencegrl.co.uk/conferences">Nessa the Chemist&#39;s Conference Database</a>: A curated list, mostly focused on organic and automation chemistry.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="research_tools">Research Tools</h3>
<ul>
<li><p><a href="https://openalex.org/">OpenAlex</a>: A powerful open source catalogue of scientific publications with an free API.</p>
</li>
<li><p><a href="https://www.connectedpapers.com/">Connected Papers</a>: An online tool for literature searching. Provide one paper &#40;<em>e.g.</em>, through a digital object identifier or DOI&#41; and see what related papers you might want to look at&#33;</p>
</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="equipment_and_techniques">Equipment and Techniques</h3>
<ul>
<li><p><a href="https://cloudlab.cmu.edu/">The CMU Cloud Lab</a>: Learn about the available equipment and get trained to use the software interface.</p>
</li>
<li><p><a href="https://cmu.edu/engineering/trace.html">Tartan Research Advanced Computing Environment &#40;TRACE&#41;</a>: Information on CMU Engineering&#39;s computer cluster.</p>
</li>
</ul>
 ]]>
  </content:encoded>
    
  <pubDate>Thu, 13 Jun 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>  
  
  
  <atom:author>
    <atom:name>The CoReACTER; Evan Walter Clark Spotte-Smith</atom:name>
  </atom:author>
        
</item>
</channel></rss>